<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The chariot and horsemen of Israel A discourse of prayer: shewing what it is, as also the meanes to attaine to the practise of it. An exercise so rare in the world, and yet so requisite, as few vse it aright, and none may omit it. By Henry Langley, minister of the Word of God, at Treswell in the county of Nottingham.</title>
            <author>Langley, Henry, d. 1636.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05061</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15202</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108258</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843930</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843930</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8696</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05061)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8696)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1209:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The chariot and horsemen of Israel A discourse of prayer: shewing what it is, as also the meanes to attaine to the practise of it. An exercise so rare in the world, and yet so requisite, as few vse it aright, and none may omit it. By Henry Langley, minister of the Word of God, at Treswell in the county of Nottingham.</title>
                  <author>Langley, Henry, d. 1636.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston, for Edmund Weauer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8696:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8696:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHARIOT and Horſemen of ISRAEL. A Diſcourſe of Prayer: ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what it is, as alſo the meanes to attaine to the practiſe of it. AN EXERCISE SO RARE in the world, and yet ſo requiſite, as few vſe it aright, and none may omit it.</p>
            <p>By HENRY LANGLEY, Miniſter of the Word of God, at <hi>Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> in the County of <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingham.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>IAM. 4.2,3,</bibl> 
               <p>—Ye fight and warre, yet ye haue not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye aske not.</p> 
               <p>Yee aske and receiue not, becauſe yee aske amiſſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON, Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngston,</hi> for <hi>Edmund Weauer.</hi> 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8696:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8696:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE EDMVND Lord SHEFFEILD, Knight of the most Noble Order of the Garter, Lord Preſident of his Maieſties learned Counſell eſtabliſhed in the North, and Lord Lieutenant there; Grace and Peace in Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here be two points (Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) as witneſſeth that worthie Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cic. Offic. lib.</hi> 2.</note>, to bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in committing things to publique view. That they bee not <hi>ſatis nota,</hi> ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly knowne before: and that they bee <hi>Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitione digna,</hi> worthie to bee knowne.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:8696:3"/>If the firſt, they are tedious: If not the ſecond, they are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious. If either, idle at the leaſt, if not naught. If both, both idle and naught.</p>
            <p>I hope, this little <hi>Treatiſe</hi> need feare iuſt exception on neither part. Many (I confeſſe) haue written on this <hi>Subiect:</hi> and iuſtly may it bee asked, what I haue found, which in their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned labours hath not alreadie been brought to light: yet dare I profeſſe, that this ſmall <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate, (abſit inuidia verbo)</hi> will affoord, vnto the illiterate ſome things, for manner at the leaſt, if not likewiſe for matter, worth the reading.</p>
            <p>And for Prayer, The nature of it is high, it being a peculiar fruite of the Spirit, the Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities great, the power won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull, and the profit incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable. <pb facs="tcp:8696:3"/> As, did not this ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding diſcourſe ſhew it, I could diſcouer at large. In a word, <hi>It is the Chariot and Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why want wee neceſſaries for ſoule and body; ſeeing the earth is the Lords, yea, the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens and the Heauen of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens: and our God is abundant in goodneſſe and truth? Wee pray not. Why are we, with <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim,</hi> in croſſes, as a cake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned<note n="b" place="margin">Hoſ. 7.8.</note>? We pray not. Why are the Heauens as braſſe, and the earth as yron? Why is there ſuch decay, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yeere to yeere, in our ſtocke, and complaining in our ſtreetes? We pray not.</p>
            <p>For could the carnall man pray: and did the man already regenerate, vſe this dutie, as hee ought: mercies would be more plentifull, iudgements not ſo <pb facs="tcp:8696:4"/> vſuall, and the rod of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked would not bee ſuffered to lie ſo long vpon the lot of the righteous.</p>
            <p>Requiſite is it therefore, and of ſpeciall conſequence, that wee learne this great leſſon, (taught ſo carefully of <hi>Iohn</hi> to his diſciples: and begged ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, of Chriſt, by his diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples: I meane) <hi>How to pray.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Doctrine is here hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the which out of my thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full remembrance of the many fauours receiued from your Lordſhip, for my quiet libertie in my Miniſtrie, and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as alſo in reſpect of the reuerend opinion, which the Church of God hath a long time (and I hope ſhall haue oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to doe no leſſe vnto the end) conceiued of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippes Chriſtian affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <pb facs="tcp:8696:4"/> God and godlineſſe, I do humbly dedicate vnto your Honour.</p>
            <q>Now the God of peace,<note n="c" place="margin">Heb.
13.20,21.</note> that brought againe, from the dead, our Lord Ieſus, the great Shepheard of the ſheepe, through the blood of the euerlaſting couenant, make you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in euery good worke to doe his will, working in you that which is well-pleaſing in his ſight, through Ieſus Chriſt, to whom be glorie for euer and euer, Amen.</q>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours in the Lord moſt humbly HENRY LANGLEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="outline">
            <pb facs="tcp:8696:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8696:5"/>
            <head>The particulars of this <hi>Diſcourſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>I. The definition, ſhewing what prayer is.</item>
                  <item>II. The Notation, whence the terme is fetched, in Hebrew.</item>
                  <item>III. The Genus of Prayer, <hi>viz.</hi> Inuocation: and what Prayer hath in commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the other kinds of Inuocation: the which are, 
<list>
                        <item>An Oath.</item>
                        <item>A Vow.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>IV. What it chalengeth to it ſelf in ſpeciall: noted here, handled after, in the doctrine of the forme, more at large.</item>
                  <item>V. How God is our Father, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as the Obiect of Prayer.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:8696:6"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>The Cauſes of Prayer, or the things whereby Prayer commeth to be that which it is. And they are foure: 
<list>
                        <item>I. The Efficient: and therein, 
<list>
                              <item>1. The maine efficient, and that in reſpect of both the 
<list>
                                    <item>Forme of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</item>
                                    <item>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</item>
                                 </list> Where is handled the ſtate of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>option, in which euery one that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, is of neceſſitie, to ſtand; becauſe, otherwiſe, God becommeth not fit to bee prayed to: Man fit to pray: nor the things wee want, fit to bee prayed for.</item>
                              <item>2. The Motiues working from 
<list>
                                    <item>Within.</item>
                                    <item>Without.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>3. The meanes of performance: and they ſuch as doe 
<list>
                                    <item>Fit vs before.</item>
                                    <item>Serue in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance.</item>
                                    <item>Further.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <pb facs="tcp:8696:6"/>II. The Matter, whereon our prayers are made, and of praying, or of exhibiting our prayers to God.</item>
                        <item>III. The Forme, the ſoule of prayer, ministring life vnto it. And therein is conſidered Faiths two-fold worke. 
<list>
                              <item>1. The one whereby wee are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the promiſes, as they are true in Christ, ſo doe they concerne vs.</item>
                              <item>2. And wee ſhall haue theſe requests, put vp according to his will.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>IV. The Ends, or wherefore wee doe pray: and they are conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, 
<list>
                              <item>1. Either ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie,</item>
                              <item>2. Or in reſpect of, 
<list>
                                    <item>God the father.</item>
                                    <item>Chriſt.</item>
                                    <item>The holy Ghoſt.</item>
                                    <item>The Word.</item>
                                    <item>Our ſelues.</item>
                                    <item>Prayer.</item>
                                    <item>The things our prayers doe concerne.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:8696:7"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>The Effects of prayer: conſidered in regard of, 
<list>
                        <item>1. God.</item>
                        <item>2. The things aimed at.</item>
                        <item>3. Our ſelues.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>The Subiect of Prayer: and that, 
<list>
                        <item>I. Receiuing: the which is, 
<list>
                              <item>Mentall.</item>
                              <item>Verball.</item>
                              <item>Locall.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>II. Whereabout Prayer is exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in, 
<list>
                              <item>Things.</item>
                              <item>Perſons. Where is handled, 
<list>
                                    <item>For whom, we are to pray.</item>
                                    <item>Through whom, we are to pray.</item>
                                    <item>To whom, we are to pray.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>And there withall is ſhewed, how we are, 
<list>
                              <item>1. To conceiue of God, in prayer.</item>
                              <item>2. To direct our prayers to him.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:8696:7"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>The Adiuncts of Prayer, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, 
<list>
                        <item>I. Simply.</item>
                        <item>II. In reſpect of theſe foure things, <hi>viz.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>The perſon pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</item>
                              <item>The Ends of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</item>
                              <item>The Subiect.</item>
                              <item>The Time.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>The diſtribution of Prayer, into, 
<list>
                        <item>I. The parts: the which are, 
<list>
                              <item>Confeſſion.</item>
                              <item>Petition.</item>
                              <item>Thankeſgiuing.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>II. The kinds: conſidered in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of, the 
<list>
                              <item>Effects of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</item>
                              <item>Subiect of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</item>
                              <item>Obiect of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head> 
            <pb facs="tcp:8696:8"/> 
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8696:8"/>THE CHARIOT and Horſemen of ISRAEL.</head>
         <div type="preface">
            <head>The Preface</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aſter, ſay the Diſciples to our Sauiour, teach vs to pray,<note n="a" place="margin">Luke
11.1.</note> as <hi>Iohn</hi> alſo taught his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Whence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, that though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Holy Ghoſt be our ſchoolemaſter, teaching vs what to pray as we ſhould: yet, for the guiding our deſires in things warrantable, expreſſing our mindes in fitting termes, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>triuing our matter in order and forme; In a word, for the doctrine of prayer, we may and ſhould bee helped, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee are defectiue, by ordinarie meanes.</p>
            <p>I haue, therefore, aduentured vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <pb n="2" facs="tcp:8696:9"/> it. A <hi>Subiect,</hi> as worthie to bee well knowne: ſo no leſſe weightie to be throughly handled.</p>
            <p>My purpoſe is not to enter into any large diſcourſe: but ſummarily to runne ouer theſe ſixe heads fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing: namely,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of this diſcourſe.</note>The
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Definition,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Cauſes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Effects,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Subiects,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Adiuncts,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>Distribution,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> of Prayer.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. I. The definition of prayer.</head>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">The Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note>Prayer is a calling vpon the name of God, as a Father.</q>
            <p>THis may bee the definition of prayer. Wherin two things are to be conſidered. 
<list>
                  <item>I. The thing defined.</item>
                  <item>II. The definition it ſelfe.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>1. The thing defined.</head>
               <p>The thing here defined, is <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er:</hi> 
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:8696:9"/> which, in Hebrew, commeth of a word which ſignifieth <hi>iudgment.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>For a man apprehending the wrath of God due for ſinne, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt ſinners, runneth to the Lord: as we may ſee in <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 32.5.</note> 
                  <hi>I acknowledged</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>my ſinne vnto thee, and mine iniquitie haue I not hid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, comming to intreatie, it ſheweth plainly, that hee can aske nothing, as of due. In like manner, giuing thankes for bleſſings recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, it argues mercie, and ſecludes merit. <hi>For to him that worketh,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle)<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 4.4.</note> 
                  <hi>the wages are not counted by fauour, but by debt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, Prayer is a pleading be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God. <hi>If</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eli</hi> to his ſonnes)<note n="d" place="margin">1. Sam. 2.25</note> 
                  <hi>one man ſinne against another, the Magistrates ſhall iudge him: but if a man ſinne againſt the Lord, who ſhall intreate for him, or pleade for him?</hi> Now, in prayer, wee pleade three things. 
<list>
                     <item>I. The Fathers gracious promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in his Sonne Chriſt. As <hi>Dauid,</hi> 
                        <pb n="4" facs="tcp:8696:10"/> 
                        <note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 89.49.</note>
                        <hi>Lord, where are thy former louing kindneſſes, ſworne to Dauid in thy truth?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item> II. The great Charter purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Ieſus Chriſt, for all his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. <hi>If ye ſhall aske any thing</hi> (ſaith Chriſt)<note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. 14.14.</note> 
                        <hi>in my name, I will doe it.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item> III. The graces of the Spirit: as the tokens and ſignes of thoſe to whom all the former belong. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member now, O Lord, I beſeech thee,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Hezekiah</hi>)<note n="g" place="margin">Iſai. 38.3.</note> 
                        <hi>how I haue wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked before thee in truth, and with a perfect heart, and haue done that which is good in thy ſight.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> But Prayer was required of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</hi> And how could he pray; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing neither ſinne to confeſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee had not falne, nor Chriſt to plead?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Yet <hi>Adam,</hi> euen in his innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, ſhould haue iudged himſelfe to haue been, but a creature, for work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip; duſt and aſhes, for matter; and for place, a ſubiect: and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer good thing his good God beſtowed vpon him, it came out of 
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8696:10"/> his ſpeciall grace and bountie. And his plea, then, was the couenant of workes. And thus much for the thing defined.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. 2. What pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er hath in common.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. The defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it ſelfe.</note>The <hi>Definition</hi> it ſelfe followeth. Wherein wee may conſider two things. 
<list>
                     <item>I. The <hi>Genus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. The <hi>Forme.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>That, is in theſe words, <hi>A calling vpon the name of God.</hi> This, in the words following, <hi>As a Father.</hi> The former it hath common to it, with both an oath and a vow: The latter it doth chalenge to it ſelf, in proper.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prayer,</hi> then, is an <hi>inuocating</hi> or <hi>calling vpon.</hi> Many and great pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges hath the Lord beſtowed on his Church: whereof this is not the leaſt, that fraile man may haue acceſſe vnto his God, and he not be moleſted with his many and rude requeſts.</p>
               <p>For which cauſe (doubtleſſe) <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> glorieth in his tongue, aboue all <pb n="6" facs="tcp:8696:11"/> his other parts: it being an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſo glorious a worke as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with God. <hi>O God</hi>
(ſaith he)<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 108.1.</note> 
                  <hi>my heart is fixed: I will ſing and giue praiſe, euen with my glorie.</hi> So Pſal.
30.12.</p>
               <p>Inuocation conſiſteth in, 
<list>
                     <item>I. A lifting vp of the minde vnto God.</item>
                     <item>II. A fixing of the minde vpon God.</item>
                     <item>III. A pouring out our minde before God.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The kindes of Inuocation are three. 
<list>
                     <item>I. Prayer.</item>
                     <item>II. An Oath.</item>
                     <item>III. A Vow,</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Prayer is a calling vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of God, as a Father. As hath been before defined.</p>
               <p>An Oath is a calling vpon the name of God, as ſupreme Iudge.</p>
               <p>A Vow is a calling vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of God, as dread Soueraigne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§. 3. What it chalengeth to it ſelfe in proper.</head>
               <p>That which Prayer chalengeth <pb n="7" facs="tcp:8696:11"/> to it ſelfe, in proper, is, that it is a calling vpon the name of God, <hi>as a Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
                  </label> But Prayer commeth of a word which ſignifieth <hi>iudgement:</hi> how, then, can it bee a calling vpon the name of God, as a Father?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I anſwere: The Lord is herein to be conſidered in his both mercie and iuſtice. In regard whereof hee is in a diuers reſpect, that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which we appeale, and to which.</p>
               <p>And ſo, by confeſſion, cleering his iuſtice, we appeale from iuſtice to mercy, which admitteth vs in our Mediatour.</p>
               <p>In whom we finde the Lord not a Iudge, but a Father. Before whom we plead (as I haue in part ſhewed before) the promiſe in his Chriſt, our elder-brother, ſhewing him our hands<note n="i" place="margin">Gen.
27.22.</note> couered with the skinne of the ſpotleſſe Lambe, euen the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Spirit, the liuely tokens of our birth-right.</p>
               <p>But vpon this may bee made a double reply. 
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reply. </seg>1</label> It ſeemeth, then, may 
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8696:12"/> ſome ſay, that part of praier, namely, <hi>confeſſion,</hi> is made to God as Iudge.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> No: Euen whiles wee confeſſe our ſinnes and vnworthineſſe, wee conſider the Lord as a Father. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prodigal ſonne cried, <hi>I haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> he called <hi>Father. Father</hi> (ſaith he)<note n="k" place="margin">Luk. 15.21.</note> 
                  <hi>I haue ſinned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reply. </seg>2</label> But when we confeſſe our ſinnes and miſery, we conſider the Lord in his iuſtice?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> We confeſſe to God, in his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, in his Chriſt, our gracious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, what hee might bee vnto vs in his iuſtice:</p>
               <p>Namely, that if hee ſhould lay iudgement to the rule, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe to the balance, wee were not able to anſwere one of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand euils committed againſt him, by vs, euen vs, who haue this free and hopeful acceſſe to come before him, and crie, <hi>Abba Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a word: To haue what to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, wee conſider the Lord in his iuſtice: but, as wee doe confeſſe theſe things, wee conſider him in <pb n="9" facs="tcp:8696:12"/> his mercie, euen our Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> But yet, you will ſay, when wee pray againſt our aduerſaries, wee conſider the Lord (and ſo pray to him) as ſupreme Iudge; as <hi>Dauid</hi> in the Pſalmes,<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 35.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Plead my cauſe, O Lord, with them that ſtriue with me: fight againſt them that fight againſt me?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Wee conſider the Lord, in ſuch petitions, in a twofold reſpect. I. Of our wrongs and wrongers. And ſo wee conceiue him as a Iudge, to whom all vengeance belongeth. II. As wee doe, by prayer, commit this caſe of wrong to him. And ſo we conceiue him as a Father.</p>
               <p>We pray to him, then, as a Father: deſiring, that hee as a Father, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our prayer, would, as a Iudge,<note n="m" place="margin">2. Chro. 6.39.</note> plead our cauſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>§. 4. How the terme, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is taken in the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
               <p>Let vs now come to the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the terme, <hi>Father.</hi> And the Lord God is a Father, in three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of relation. 
<list>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:8696:13"/>
                     <item>I. By generation.</item>
                     <item>II. By Creation.</item>
                     <item>III. By Adoption.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>By Generation, hee is onely the Father of Chriſt, his onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: euen as his type <hi>Iſaac</hi> was the onely lawfull-begotten of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> by <hi>Sarah.</hi> And therefore hee ſaith not to his Diſciples, ioyntly, <hi>I goe to our Father:</hi> but diſtinctly, <hi>I goe to my Father,</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Ioh. 20.17</note> 
                  <hi>and to your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> A Father to both: but in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers reſpects: to him by generation, to them by adoption.</p>
               <p>By Creation God is a Father to all his creatures. <hi>One God and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle.<note n="o" place="margin">Epheſ.
4.6.</note> And <hi>Adam</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Luk. 3.</note> is called the ſonne of God.</p>
               <p>But, Father, is not ſo taken here. The couenant is broken on our parts, and his image is defaced. And there is no ſpecialtie of creation that will hold plea: but all make di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt vs.</p>
               <p>Therfore, in the third place, God is a Father, by adoption: <hi>viz.</hi> to that peculiar companie which is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <pb n="11" facs="tcp:8696:13"/> to the election of grace; who hold all things by vertue of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelicall couenant: hauing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed the vnwarrantable right of Creation, and ſued out a fine of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie, from God, in Ieſus Chriſt, by heartie prayer, and faith vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>Adoption is to make choice of another mans child to be ours, and ſo to make him our heire, or ioynt-heire. Now, wee were all eſtranged and cut off from God, in <hi>Adam:</hi> and became the baſtards of that grand-Fornicatour the Diuell, and old Strumpet the world. Inſomuch, that wee muſt all confeſſe, that our firſt Father was an Amorite, and our Mother a Hittite,<note n="q" place="margin">Ezek. 16.3.</note>.</p>
               <p>But it pleaſed the Lord, to chuſe, out of this forlorne companie, a number to himſelfe, to make them a holy nation, a royall Prieſthood, a peculiar people, euen partakers of the adoption of Sonnes.</p>
               <p>Here then, by Father, is meant, God in Chriſt, who hath in him, 
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8696:14"/> I. Choſen vs before time. II. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed vs in time. III. And made vs, in part, perſonally partakers of both: abounding toward vs, in all wiſedome and prudence:<note n="r" place="margin">Eph. 1.8.9.</note> hauing made knowne vnto vs the myſterie of his will.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. II. The cauſes of Prayer.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Cauſes of prayer.</note>THe Cauſes of Prayer, are foure. 
<list>
                  <item>I. The Efficient.</item>
                  <item>II. The Matter.</item>
                  <item>III. The Forme.</item>
                  <item>IV. The End.</item>
               </list> 
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>I. Efficient.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The maine Efficient in reſpect of, 1. The Forme. 2. The Matter. Euery one that praieth, muſt ſtand in the ſtate of election: the which maketh, 1. The Lord fit to be praied to. 2. The perſon fit to pray. 3 The things fit to be praied for, &amp;c.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The Efficient, or cauſe making prayer, is Principall, or leſſe-princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall. The leſſe-principall is either Impulſiue, or adiuuant. Here, then, are three things to bee handled, in generall. 
<list>
                     <item>I. The Main-efficient.</item>
                     <item>II. The Motiues.</item>
                     <item>III. The meanes of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance.</item>
                  </list> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:8696:14"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The Principall, or maine-effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of Prayer, in reſpect of the Forme, is the Spirit of God, by his grace teaching and enabling, yea, praying in vs, Rom. 8.26.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The Principall Efficient, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the matter, is the Perſon praying. Who, in reſpect of the Lawes exaction, is euery man. All are bound to pray. Want of grace doth diſable, but exempt none.</p>
               <p>But in reſpect of ability, it is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the elect called, iuſtified and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified: In a word, The adopted ones of God.</p>
               <p>In which ſtate that euerie one muſt ſtand which prayeth, we may ſee, if we conſider the vſe of it, in reſpect of, 
<list>
                     <item>I. The Obiect God, to whom we pray.</item>
                     <item>II. The Perſon praying.</item>
                     <item>III. The Things deſired in Prayer.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For the Firſt, Not God ſimply, but God a Father, reconciled and made at one with vs, is our obiect. <pb n="14" facs="tcp:8696:15"/> And therefore not being within A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, there is no right relation betweene God and vs.</p>
               <p>This was intimated by the vaile,<note n="a" place="margin">Exod.
24.</note> which excluded the people of the Iewes out of the <hi>Holy of Holies.</hi> Into the which (ſaith the Apoſtle)<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 10.16.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee haue liberty to enter, in the bloud of Ieſus, by the new and liuing way, which he hath prepared for vs, through the vaile, that is to ſay, his fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heere wee may take notice of three faults in prayer.</p>
               <p n="1">I. Many pray to the Lord: but put no difference betweene his <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in himſelfe, and what hee is to his Church in Chriſt. But, ſo they pray to God, it ſerues.</p>
               <p n="2"> II. Many conceiuing aright of God, in generall, as a Father, are not perſwaded, neither labour to be perſwaded, in ſpeciall, that he is their Father. They hope well: but naught can they beleeue. They but goe to God by heare-ſay.</p>
               <p n="3"> III. Some doe perſwade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, <pb n="15" facs="tcp:8696:15"/> that God is their Father. Not from the earneſt of the Spirit: but rather from the ignorance of ſinne, want of due examination, and from carnall preſumption.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, This Adoption is of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute vſe, in reſpect of the Perſon praying. Becauſe,</p>
               <p n="1">I. Hence ariſeth his abilitie, to call God Father, and poure out his heart aright before him. For other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as there is an <hi>antipathy</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Lord and his heart: ſo likewiſe, hee wanteth that new tongue, requiſite in euery one that would cal vpon the Lord: without which his wordes are barbarous, and not of the right <hi>dialect</hi> of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan. For which cauſe the Lord calleth the Iewes crying, <hi>howling</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Hoſ. 7.14.</note>.</p>
               <p n="2"> II. Without this Adoption, his Perſon is in diſgrace: and his offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring muſt needs be reiected, as 
<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 4.</note>
                  <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ins</hi> was.</p>
               <p n="3"> III. Heereby wee are made fit obiects of Gods bleſſings. The which we are not, vnleſſe we be his <pb n="16" facs="tcp:8696:16"/> adopted ones, called &amp;c. For,</p>
               <p n="1">I. Otherwiſe the Lord hath made no promiſe to vs. <hi>If ye abide in mee</hi> (ſaith Chriſt<note n="e" place="margin">Ioh.
15.7.</note>) <hi>and my words abide in you: yee ſhall aske what yee will, and it ſhall be done for you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2"> II. Otherwiſe we haue no part in Chriſts Prayer. <hi>I pray for them</hi> (ſaith Chriſt)<note n="f" place="margin">Ioh.
15.7.20.</note>, <hi>I pray not for the world:</hi> and who they are, wee may ſee after; <hi>Neither,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>pray I for theſe alone, but for them alſo, which ſhall beleeue on mee through their word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3"> III. The Lord giueth all things for the glory of his name. Now, wouldſt thou not willingly giue a man a ſtaffe to ſtrike thy ſelfe with? And canſt thou looke that GOD will giue thee any good thing, to diſhonour him withal, whiles thou art out of Chriſt, called, and like a diſtempered ſtomacke, turns whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome meat into noyſome humors?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Laſtly, by the vertue of this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>option, the things wee deſire and want, are made fit obiects to bee <pb n="17" facs="tcp:8696:16"/> prayed for, being all of them par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of our ſpirituall inheritance, as alſo, ſuch as with comfort, we may be thankefull for.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. 2. The <hi>Impulſiue,</hi> or <hi>mouing cauſe</hi> worketh from within, or from without.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. 1. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within. 2. From with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Thoſe which worke from within, inciting and mouing vs to praier, are,
<list>
                     <item>I. Conſcience of our duty: as prayer is commanded vs by God.</item>
                     <item>II. Loue of God: as it is a confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with God.</item>
                     <item>III. Zeale: as it is a ſacrifice to God.</item>
                     <item>IV. A Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian loue of our ſelues: as by it we receiue ſupply from God.</item>
                     <item>V. Hope: as we haue a promiſe to be heard of God.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> How commeth it to be peculiar to grace, to moue vs to pray: and that nature hath no hand in it?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I anſwere: I. Nature, in our wants, reſpecteth naturall inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, as they endanger the ſtate of the outward man. Grace loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <pb n="18" facs="tcp:8696:17"/> higher, and conceiueth, in theſe, the chaſtiſement of God, with many ſpirituall euils. II. Nature, vpon the ſight of our wants, ſtirreth vs vp to vſe naturall meanes: and if to praier, yet as morally conſidered, as the Philoſopher cried, <hi>Being of beings haue mercie vpon mee!</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ens entium miſerere mei!</hi>
                  </note> But grace draweth vs vnto GOD in Chriſt: vſing ſecondary meanes, in ſubmiſſion to his commaund, for conſcience ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The <hi>Impulſiue</hi> cauſes working from without, and ſtirring vs vp to prayer, are eſpecially theſe:</p>
               <p n="1">I. The word of God: and it mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs three waies: namely, by, I. Commandement. II. Promiſe. III. Examples of the children of God, and aboue all, of Chriſt our <hi>Head,</hi> therein recorded.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Our miſerable condition, by reaſon of ſinne: as namely, I. Our wants: that of our ſelues wee haue nothing. II. Our weakneſſe: that by our ſelues wee can get nothing. III. Our vnworthineſſe: that for <pb n="19" facs="tcp:8696:17"/> ourſelues, that is, our owne ſakes, we can looke for nothing.</p>
               <p n="3">III. The worth of prayer: whoſe, 
<list>
                     <item>1. Priuiledge,</item>
                     <item>2. Power,</item>
                     <item>3. Profit,</item>
                  </list>is exceeding great: as we may ſee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. Accidents of mercie and iudgement, which befall vs. As, at the deliuerance of Iſrael, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> &amp; his hoſte were ouerthrowne in the ſea,<note n="g" place="margin">Exod. 15.1,2, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> and the children of Iſrael praiſed the Lord. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the children of <hi>Ammon</hi> and <hi>Moab</hi> and mount <hi>Seir</hi> came againſt <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat,</hi> hee proclaimed a faſt,<note n="h" place="margin">2. Chron. 20.3,4,5, &amp;c.</note> and <hi>Iudah</hi> gathered themſelues toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to aske helpe of the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§. 3. The meanes of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance:</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>and they, ſuch as doe, 1. Fit vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. 2. Serue in the performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. 3. Further.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The Adiuuant or helping cauſes, are ſuch as doe, 
<list>
                     <item>I. Fit vs before.</item>
                     <item>II. Serue in the performance.</item>
                     <item>III. Further.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The things that doe before hand <pb n="20" facs="tcp:8696:18"/> 
fit vs for prayer, are, I. The word of God, in generall. II. More parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, the Lords Prayer. The Formes of godly affected men hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping withall. III. Meditation.</p>
               <p>And we are to meditate eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of three things. I. Of God, in himſelfe, and in his couenant to vs. II. Of our own eſtate. III. Of the manner of pouring out our hearts before God, by prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The benefits of Meditation, in this caſe, are eſpecially theſe: I. It affoordeth matter. II. It prepareth the mind. III. It poſſeſſeth vs bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with that which we are to exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite to the Lord: and ſo maketh way for affection. IV. It rangeth vs within compaſſe.</p>
               <p>The helping cauſes of vſe, in the performance, are the inſtruments therein vſed. The which are either naturall, or ſpirituall.</p>
               <p>The naturall are three: I. The heart conceiuing or conſenting. II, The minde contriuing. III. The mouth vttering.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:8696:18"/>The ſpiritual inſtrument, is <hi>faith.</hi> 
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 10.14.</note>
                  <hi>How ſhall they call on him, in whom they haue not beleeued?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The things that doe further vs in prayer, are, I. The prayers of the Church for vs. And for this cauſe the Prophet and King <hi>Dauid</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth a Pſalme to the people, to be vſed for him. Wherein they are taught to ſay, 
<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 20.2,3,4.</note>
                  <hi>The Lord heare thee, &amp;c.</hi> When <hi>Moſes</hi> his hands were heauy,<note n="l" place="margin">Exod. 17.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> ſtaied them. II. Faſting. <hi>Defraud not one another</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle)<note n="m" place="margin">1. Cor. 7.5.</note> 
                  <hi>except it be with conſent for a time, that yee may giue your ſelues to fasting and prayer.</hi> So <hi>Anna</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Luke 2.</note> ſerued God with faſtings and prayers.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> Are all bound to faſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <label>The vſe of faſting.</label> In a generall humiliation, vnder Gods iudgements, it is moſt meete that all ſhould faſt. For, though fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting be not ſimply required, as of the eſſence of the dutie to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: yet it is required, by ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitable conſequence, as an appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix. For, I. The Lord requireth, in 
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8696:19"/> ſuch caſes,<note n="o" place="margin">Ierem. 8.6.</note> a due conſideration of his iudgement for ſinne, and that out of his deepe diſpleaſure. II. He requireth, then, a thorough humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation. His ſacrifice, muſt bee at all times (much more at that time) <hi>a broken</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 51.17.</note> 
                  <hi>and a contrite hart.</hi> III. We ſhould iudge our ſelues, that we be not iudged of the Lord. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King of Niniue commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,<note n="q" place="margin">Ion. 3.5,7.</note> not onely that men ſhould faſt: but withall, that <hi>neither beast, heard nor flocke, ſhould taste anie thing, feed nor drinke water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But for our ordinarie conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, touching both perſons and times, I anſwere with the Apoſtle,<note n="r" place="margin">Rom.
14.17</note> 
                  <hi>The kingdome of God is not meate and drinke: but righteouſneſſe and peace, and ioy in the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Earthly foode is ſubordinate to theſe. If therfore, meate and drinke further righteouſnes, &amp;c. wee may, nay we muſt, eate and drinke. But if they hinder, or if abſtinence would further: as there is a time to eate, ſo we muſt finde a time to faſt.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:8696:19"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> Whether is it lawfull to eate, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of a faſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> If otherwiſe wee be not able to continue, wee may. The Apoſtles poſition is our warrant: <hi>The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God is not meate and drinke.</hi> Alwaies prouided, that the meate, for both quantitie and qualitie, doe argue meere neceſſitie. When <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> his hands were heauie,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Exod. 17.8, &amp;c.</note> he vſeth meanes of helpe. But what? ſuch as did affoord neither ſtate nor plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. They tooke a ſtone, ſaith the text, and put it vnder him, and hee ſate thereon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>§. 4.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>II. Materiall: and, I. Of Prayer: and 1. The firſt matter. 2. The ſecond or propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. II. Of praying.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>We come now to the matter. And that of Prayer, and of Praying.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> The matter of praier is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, as the firſt, or as the ſecond or proportioned matter.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt matter of Prayer conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in the deſires of our hearts. <hi>Poure out</hi>
(ſaith the Pſalmiſt)<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 62.8.</note> 
                  <hi>your heart before him.</hi> And againe,<note n="u" place="margin">Pſal.
38.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord all my deſire is before thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:8696:20"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond or proportioned mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of prayer conſiſteth in theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and motions of the heart, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triued in that forme wherein wee doe fit our ſelues, to make our caſe knowne vnto, and to deale with, the Lord, in this holy dutie.</p>
               <p>And though the Lord do pleaſe; in his Chriſt, to heare faithfull prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, bee it neuer ſo confuſed: yet ſhould we labour to performe it in the beſt manner. For our God is the God of order.</p>
               <p>Now, (not to tye thee (Reader) to one ſtrict forme: but yet, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe a few rules, that thou maiſt at the leaſt, pray in ſome forme) for thy direction, if herein thou beeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue, conſider theſe eight parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars following.</p>
               <p>I. Propound God in Chriſt, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him forth ſo, in words, as thou art taught, to conceiue of him, in the Scriptures: and as beſt befit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thy caſe. II. Then deale con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſinne; (as that which eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially troubleth thee, and maketh <pb n="25" facs="tcp:8696:20"/> thee vnapt to ask, and vncapable to receiue any good thing) touching which thou muſt deale by way of, 1. Confeſſion of the act, and the euill both of guilt and deſert of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. 2. Petition of forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and acceptance. 3. Profeſſion of thankfulneſſe and amendment. III. Deſire ſpirituall bleſſings. All which the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Iames 1.5.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth vnder Wiſdome. IV. Then temporall. V. As wee pray for our ſelues: ſo muſt wee alſo, for others. VI. As we deſire what we want: ſo muſt we remember to bee thankfull for what we haue. VII. We may vſe reaſons, from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, examples of Gods dealings with others, our owne experience, &amp;c, to ſtrengthen our faith. VIII. As faith in the promiſe is ſhewed, in the beginning (by ſuch termes as theſe, <hi>Our gracious and merciful fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Ieſus Chriſt, &amp;c</hi>): ſo muſt our hope of the performance be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in the Concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The which is ordinarily, by this terme, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:8696:21"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> The Matter of praying conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in three things. 
<list>
                     <item>I. A lifting vp of the minde vnto God. <hi>Let vs lift vp</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ieremy</hi>) <hi>our heart with our hands,</hi>
                        <note n="x" place="margin">Lam. 3.41.</note> 
                        <hi>vnto GOD in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. A fixing of the minde vpon GOD. <hi>Vnto thee</hi>
(ſaith the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt<note n="y" place="margin">Pſ. 123.1.2.</note>) <hi>lift I vp mine eyes: O thou that dwelleſt in the heauens. Behold, as the eyes of ſeruants, looke vnto the hand of their maſters, and as the eyes of a maiden, vnto the hand of her miſtreſſe: ſo our eyes waite vpon the Lord our God, vntil that he haue mercy vpon vs.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. A pouring out of our hearts before the Lord. <hi>Truſt in him, at all times, ye peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt<note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 62.8.</note>), <hi>poure out your heart before him.</hi> Againe,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſ. 142.2.</note> 
                        <hi>I poured out my complaint before him: I ſhewed before him my trouble.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>§. 5.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> III. The forme of prayer. Faiths dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble worke, in praier. Three de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, of this latter worke of faith.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The <hi>Forme</hi> of Prayer, is in theſe words, <hi>as a Father,</hi> as hath beene ſhewed before, in the definition.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:8696:21"/>And it conſiſteth in the <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and application</hi> of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes made to vs in Ieſus Chriſt, as appeareth by that of the Pſalmiſt,<note n="b" place="margin">Pſ. 62.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Truſt in him at all times, ye people, poure out your hart before him:</hi> and of <hi>Iames,</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Iam. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>But let him aske in faith, nothing wauering.</hi> 
And heerein faith performeth a double worke.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I. The one is, wherby we are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that the promiſes, as they are true in themſelues, being in Chriſt, <hi>yea,</hi> and in him <hi>Amen:</hi> ſo doe they belong vnto vs, as the adopted ſonnes of God. And in this reſpect Chriſt teacheth vs, in his Prayer, to beginne with <hi>our Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> II. The other is, whereby wee aſſure our hearts, that through Chriſt, in theſe our requeſts put vp according to his will, we are heard of God: and ſhall haue, yea haue, the requeſts that we haue deſired of him. And therefore Chriſt teacheth vs, in his Prayer, to conclude with <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And of this latter worke of Faith, <pb n="28" facs="tcp:8696:22"/> 
there are three degrees.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I. The firſt is, to carry our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to the Angell,<note n="d" place="margin">Reuel. 8.</note> to bee put into the golden Cenſor. That is, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to our prayers, the powerful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of Ieſus Chriſt, our High Prieſt ouer the houſe of God: aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our ſelues, that it is able to make ſupply of all our wants: that much incenſe, wherewith he is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, being giuen vnto him, that hee might offer it with the prayers of all the Saints.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> II. To ſee our prayers <hi>euaporate and fume vp,</hi> out of the Angels hand, in the ſmoake of the incenſe, into the noſtrils of the Lord. That is, to beleeue, that, by the vertue of Chriſts interceſſion, our prayers doe moſt ſweetly aſcend before the Lord. And ſo (as it were) euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Lord looke cheereful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon vs, in his Chriſt, ſmelling a ſacrifice of peace.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> III. To heare peaceable and comfortable words fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the throne of grace. That is, to haue vpon <pb n="29" facs="tcp:8696:22"/> the former, a true and comfortable aſſurance, of the performance of what wee haue prayed for, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of petition: and of the accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of our thankefulneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>§. 6.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>IV. The End of prayer. I. In generall. II. In ſpeciall.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The ends of Prayer follow. And they are to be conſidered, 
<list>
                     <item>I. In generall, as it is a dutie.</item>
                     <item>II. In ſpeciall, as it is the dutie of Prayer.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The ends of Prayer in generall, are,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> I. The glory of God. II. The diſcharge of our dutie. III. For heauenly and comfortable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe with God. IV. That our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices might, in this as in other holy duties, be before the Lord.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> The ends of Prayer in ſpeciall, may bee referred to ſixe heads: namely, being conſidered in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of, 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>God the Father.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:8696:23"/>
                     <item>IV. <hi>The Word.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>V. <hi>Our ſelues.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>VI. <hi>Prayer it ſelfe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>VII. <hi>The things aymed at in Prayer.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The End, in regard of God the Father, is to, I. Acknowledge him the fountaine of all goodnes: from whom (as the Apoſtle witneſſeth), commeth euery good giuing, and euery perfect gift. II. For the hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing and ſanctifying of his great Name, in moſt ſpeciall manner. III. In ſubmiſſion to his ſpeciall command. In all which, the Sonne and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> are not exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: neither the Father, from them, in theſe two following.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The End, in regard of Chriſt, is, that wee might be partakers of his fulneſſe.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The End, in regard of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> is, to vſe the meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee may be pleaſed to worke in and vpon vs.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The End, in regard of the Word, is, to be partakers of the benefit of <pb n="31" facs="tcp:8696:23"/> the Goſpell, qualifying the <hi>ſeuere,</hi> (but moſt iuſt) rigour of the Law.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The Ends, in regard of our ſelues, (that is conſidered in this relation) are, I. For the ſupply of our neceſſities, and to expreſſe our thankefulneſſe, II. To diſloade our cares and troubles. III. To waken and ſtirre vp in vs, the graces of God.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The End, in reſpect of Prayer it ſelfe, is not, for the worth of it, to purchaſe any thing. But, we vſe it, in ſubmiſſion to Gods command, as a meanes whereby wee receiue and bring home to vs, the good things which Chriſt hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and God promiſed.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Laſtly, wee doe vſe it, that wee may more comfortably take, what we get for for bleſſings.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:8696:24"/>
            <head>CHAP. III. The Effects of Prayer.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Effects</hi> of Prayer follow: namely, what Prayer worketh. And they may be conſidered in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of, 
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>The things aymed at in prayer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>Our ſelues.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <argument>
                  <p>Effects con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in regard of, 1. God. 2. The things aimed at.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Prayer, conſidered in regard of God, produceth a double effect. I. It honoureth the Lord. <hi>Who ſo offereth praiſe,</hi> (ſaith the Lord)<note n="a" place="margin">Pſa. 50.23.</note> 
                  <hi>glorifieth mee.</hi> II. It preuaileth powerfully euen with the Lord himſelfe. As, to inſiſt vpon ſome particulars: I. It chaungeth the Lords threatnings: Ion. 3.8.10.11. II. It keepeth the Lord with vs. Mal.
1.10.11. III. It calleth the Lord backe, when hee is gone from vs. Exod.
33.13.14.15.16.17. IV. It turneth away his wrath, when he would in iudgement burſt <pb n="33" facs="tcp:8696:24"/> in vpon vs, Pſalm. 106.23. Ezech. 22.30.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The <hi>Effects</hi> of Prayer, in reſpect of the things aymed at, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to foure heads. I. It preuenteth the dangers that we feare. As, deſtruction<note n="b" place="margin">Ion. 3.8.10</note> from Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuee: and the ſword<note n="c" place="margin">Eſa. 38.14.15.16.17.18. &amp;c.</note> from Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem. It ſtaied<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 31.24</note> for <hi>Iacob, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans</hi> hand: and<note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 32.9.10. &amp;c.</note> aſſwaged <hi>Eſaus</hi> wrath.</p>
               <p n="2"> II. It remooueth the euils that we feele. When Iſrael groaned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their taske-maſters in Egypt, the Lord remooued their ſhoulder from the burthen,<note n="f" place="margin">Pſ. 81.6.</note> and their hands were deliuered from the pots, Pſal. 32.4.5.</p>
               <p n="3"> III. It procureth what wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. <hi>Elias,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iames,</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Iam. 5.17.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Was a man ſubiect to like paſſions, as wee are, and hee prayed earneſtly that it might not raine: and it rained not on the earth, by the ſpace of three yeeres and ſixe moneths. And hee prayed againe, and the heauen gaue raine, and the earth brought forth <pb n="34" facs="tcp:8696:25"/> her fruite.</hi> And if any man lack wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:<note n="h" place="margin">Iames 1.5.</note> he biddeth that we aske of God.</p>
               <p n="4"> IV. It ſanctifieth what we haue. <hi>Euery creature of God is good,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle,<note n="i" place="margin">1. Tim.
4.4.5</note> 
                  <hi>and nothing to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, if it be receiued with thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing: for it is ſanctified by the word of God and prayer.</hi> To bee ſhort, it can doe any thing. Phil. 4.6.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> Whence commeth it that prayer is ſo powerfull?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> Not from any thing in the work ſimply. But, I. As it is that meanes which the Lord hath appoynted, to be vſed, by his word of commaund. II. As he hath pleaſed to annex gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſes vnto it. III. As it is perfected, and hath all the wants ſupplied, by the incenſe of that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of the eternall couenant (Chriſt Ieſus): and ſo made the worthie meanes, according to Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, whereby hee may conueigh vnto vs, thorough Chriſt, the good bleſſings which he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed. IV. And as that God, to <pb n="35" facs="tcp:8696:25"/> whom wee pray, is abundant in goodneſſe and truth, and rich to all that call vpon him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. 2.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Effects con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in regard of, 3. Our ſelues.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The <hi>Effects</hi> of Prayer, in reſpect of our ſelues, may bee referred to two heads. 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>The Commodities.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>The Symptomes.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Touching the good and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble worke of Prayer, in vs. I. It is a moſt ſpeciall exerciſe, for the ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp the graces of God in vs. II. It nouriſheth, as all the graces of God, in vs, ſo eſpecially hope and patience, 1. Sam. 1.15,18. III. It fulfilleth our ioy, Ioh. 16.24.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Effects</hi> of Prayer, which, as <hi>ſymptomes</hi> and ſignes doe demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate true feeling prayer, are three. I. It cauſeth a holy heate in our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. Whereby a man findeth himſelfe, after a while, much more heauenlily affected, then in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his prayer. II. A wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from the thoughts of the <pb n="36" facs="tcp:8696:26"/> world, for the preſent, immediatly after his prayer. As hee that behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Sunne, hath not his eyes inſtantly fit to looke vpon earthlie things. And therefore, he that can, preſently after prayer, thinke and ſpeake of worldly affaires, with as much eaſe and delight, as if hee had but come from a worldly exerciſe: it is much to be doubted (to ſay no worſe) that he prayed not heartily. III. It giueth a man a heauenlie aſpect, for the preſent: making him looke like one, that hath had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe with God.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IV. The Subiect of Prayer.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Subiect</hi> of <hi>Prayer</hi> is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. 
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>Receiuing.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>Whereabout Prayer is exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <argument>
                  <p>Subiect. I. Receiuing. 1. <hi>Mentall.</hi> 2. <hi>Verball.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3. The two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer may, conſidered in another relation, be called <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuncts.</hi>
                     </note> 3. <hi>Locall:</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, in reſpect of, 1. Place. 2. Prayer.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The <hi>Subiect</hi> receiuing, is, 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>Mentall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:8696:26"/>
                     <item>II. <hi>Verball.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. <hi>Locall.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, I ſay, it is <hi>mentall,</hi> which conſiſteth in the cogitations of our mindes. For wee may conceiue a prayer, though it bee not vttered. And thoſe, which are vttered in words, were firſt in thought.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, it conſiſteth in the words, whereby wee expreſſe the motions and deſires of our hearts. And they are of great vſe, in prayer. I. That the Lord, as hee hath crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, redeemed &amp; regenerated both, might alſo be glorified by both. II. They are meanes of Chriſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, in prayer, when two or three, or more are gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the name of God. III. They further much him that prayeth, though he bee alone. For, 1. They doe repreſent more matter ſtill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his mind. 2. The vttering and mentioning of the promiſes and threatnings &amp;c. is a means to make the matter worke vpon vs.
3. They keepe the minde more attent. And <pb n="38" facs="tcp:8696:27"/> the altring and changing of our words, are herein of great vſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The laſt <hi>ſubiect-receiuing</hi> is the place. The which is to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, in regard of, 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>The place it ſelfe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>Prayer.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> All places, as places, may ſerue for prayer. <hi>Beleeue mee,</hi> ſaith our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to the woman of Samaria,<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 4.21. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>the houre commeth, when ye ſhall neither in this mountaine, nor yet at Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, worſhip the Father.—But the houre commeth, and now is, when the true worſhippers ſhall worſhippe the Father in ſpirit and truth: for the Father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him.</hi> And the Apoſtle willeth,<note n="b" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.8.</note> that <hi>men pray euery-where. Reaſ.</hi> 1. The Lord is euery-where. II. All places are Gods, and for his glorie. III. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of place was ceremoniall, pointing at Chriſt our ſpirituall Temple, in whom alone God will accept vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> But yet, the Lord is the God of order: and ſo all things are to bee <pb n="39" facs="tcp:8696:27"/> done decently, and in order. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, therefore, of prayer,</p>
               <p n="1">I. Publike prayer ſhould be in a publike place. <hi>Reaſon</hi> 1. That all might more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniently aſſemble. II. In more fitting manner to make a publike profeſsion of our faith and obedience. III. For the more liuely manifeſtation of the libertie, which (by Gods bleſsing) wee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy.</p>
               <p n="2">II. More priuate praier, (I meane of a familie) in euery familie apart. <hi>As for me and my houſe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuah</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Ioſ. 24.15.</note>), <hi>we will ſerue the Lord.</hi> III. Moſt priuate, (that is, of euery par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſon) in a ſecret place. <hi>When thou prayeſt,</hi> ſaith our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,<note n="d" place="margin">Matth. 6.6.</note> 
                  <hi>enter into thy cloſet, and when thou haſt ſhut thy doore, pray to thy Father which is in ſecret. Reaſ.</hi> I. To auoide imputations of hypocriſie. II. For the more libertie, in both word and ieſture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:8696:28"/>
               <head>§. 2.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>II. Occupying, or where about praier is exerciſed: the which is, 1. Reall. &amp;. 1. What they are. 2. How obiects 3. How farre.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The <hi>ſubiect</hi> whereabout prayer is exerciſed (which is properly the Obiect) followeth. And it is, 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>Either Reall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>Or Perſonall.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Touching the <hi>things</hi> which are the obiects of Prayer, wee may conſider, 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>What they are.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>How they are obiects of our Prayers.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. <hi>How farre.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Theſe things are, I. Such as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne either this life, or the life to come. For, 1. All muſt come from God,<note n="e" place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> 2. Righteouſneſſe hath the promiſe of both.<note n="f" place="margin">Heb.
13.5.</note> 3. We are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to goe to God<note n="g" place="margin">Iam.
1.5. Matth. 6.9.10.11. &amp;c.</note> for both. II. They are ſimply good: or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euill in themſelues, the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations reſpected in Prayer, are good. For good things we deſire, The continuance of what we haue: and the beſtowing of what wee want. And, of euill things, wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, 
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:8696:28"/> their preuention, profitable vſe, and remouall, and are anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably thankefull. III. As all good things, are our obiect, ſo all good meanes. IV. Laſtly, as all good things: ſo a bleſſing in the getting, keeping and vſing of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And all theſe are our obiect, as our inheritance. For nothing can wee deſire of the Lord, but our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance.</p>
               <p>Hence ariſeth a ſpeciall comfort in prayer. For haue wee an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? Then whatſoeuer we aske, is ours before; as we may ſee, in the Lords Prayer: where we are taught to ſay, <hi>Giue vs this day, our daily bread.</hi> When we pray, we aske our penſion. Our ſeuerall wants, are ſo many pay-daies.</p>
               <p>Many will pray willingly, when they need nothing: but in a ſtrait, they can hardly bee drawne to the Lord. Alas, they miſ-conceiue of prayer; wee can neuer pray more comfortably, then in a want, For then, and not before, commeth <pb n="42" facs="tcp:8696:29"/> the promiſe in force.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Call vpon mee, in the euill day,</hi> (ſaith the Lord<note n="h" place="margin">Pſ. 50.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>) <hi>I will deliuer thee.</hi> Marke: the meanes and the time muſt both concurre. If wee pray not for deliuerance, wee omit the meanes. And if it be not the day of trouble, when we pray, we mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake the time. So, Pſalm.
102.17. Luk. 1.53.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Laſtly, Theſe things are our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, I. Not in their purchaſe: For ſo are they the obiect of Chriſt in his humiliation. II. Nor in their receiuing at the hands of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for vs: For ſo they reſpect Chriſt in his exaltation. III. Nor yet, in their beſtowing: For ſo they are the obiect of Chriſts inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion. IV. But in our receiuing of them. For, we do not purchaſe them, but Chriſt our Sacrifice: nor receiue them immediately, but Chriſt our Head: nor obtaine the beſtowing of them, but Chriſt our High-Prieſt ouer the houſe of God. Onely, wee vſe the meanes, <pb n="43" facs="tcp:8696:29"/> on our parts, required in dutie.</p>
            </div>
            <!-- stopped -->
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. 2.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Perſonall, referred to three heads. 1. For whom.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The Perſonall Obiects follow: which may bee referred to three heads. 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>For whom</hi> we are to pray.</item>
                     <item>II. <hi>Through whom</hi> we are to pray.</item>
                     <item>III. <hi>To whom</hi> we are to pray.</item>
                  </list> 
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The Perſons for whom, are, I. Our ſelues: II. Or others. And they are all men. <hi>I exhort there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle<note n="i" place="margin">1. Tim.
2.1.</note>) <hi>that firſt of all, ſupplications, prayers, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions, and giuing of thankes bee made for all men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is, alwaies excepted, whom the Scriptures haue elſe-where ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. And they are, In whole,</p>
               <p n="1">I. Of the liuing, Such as ſinne againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> As the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle aduiſeth vs,<note n="k" place="margin">1. Ioh.
5.16</note> 
                  <hi>If any man ſee his brother ſinne, a ſinne not vnto death, he ſhall aske, and he ſhall giue him life, for them that ſinne not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death. There is a ſin vnto death, I do not ſay; that he ſhall pray for it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. The Dead are not to bee <pb n="44" facs="tcp:8696:30"/> prayed for. Becauſe, I. There is no command for it: and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, no promiſe. II. Wee haue no example, in all the Scriptures. III. <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith peremptorily,<note n="l" place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.6.</note> that they haue no portion of all that is done vnder the Sun. IV. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death, there is no change, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from Hell to Heauen, or from Heauen to Hell. As <hi>Abraham</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>Diues.</hi> And <hi>Diues</hi> deſireth not, that <hi>Lazarus</hi> might be ſent to his brethren,<note n="m" place="margin">Luk. 16.27.28.</note> to certifie them where hee was, to the end, they might pray for his deliuerance: but to warne them, (becauſe they had yet time) leaſt they came into that place of torment. Againe the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons excepted, in part, are men ſo farre as their purpoſes, plots, and practiſes are derogatorie to Gods glory, and againſt Chriſtian chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
2. Ioh. 10.12.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§. 3.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Perſonall, referred to three heads. 2. Through whom.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The perſon through whom wee are to put vp our prayers, is <hi>Ieſus <pb n="45" facs="tcp:8696:30"/> Chriſt,</hi> the Mediatour betweene God and man. And hee onely is a fit Mediatour, as the worke was to be performed, 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>For man.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>To God.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. <hi>Betweene God and man.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>He was moſt fit to be the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour for man: Becauſe, hee was <hi>man,</hi> meet to take his ſinne vpon him; and <hi>God,</hi> able to diſcharge it. <hi>Man,</hi> to vndertake his dutie: and <hi>God,</hi> able to performe it.</p>
               <p>Hee was the fitteſt to be Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour to God. Becauſe, he was <hi>man</hi> borne vnder the Law, that could be made ſubiect to the Law, and die a curſed death. And <hi>God,</hi> able to adde infinite merite, to giue the Lord infinite ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>He was the fitteſt betweene <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man.</hi> Becauſe, I. Being God, he could not but reſpect Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Being man, hee could not but bee touched with the feeling of mans miſerie. II. Being God, he hath free acceſſe to God: being <pb n="46" facs="tcp:8696:31"/> man, wee haue free acceſſe to him. III. Being <hi>God,</hi> he could preuaile with God: being man, we can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile with him. God will deny him, nothing: hee will deny, his, nothing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It was meet,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>)<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 42. <hi>Mediator au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem inter Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; homines o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portebat vt haberet ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ſimile Deo, &amp; ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ſimile hominibus: ne in vtro<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milis homini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus longè eſſet à Deo: aut in vtro<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſimilis Deo, longè eſſet ab homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ita Mediator non eſſet.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that the Mediator betweene God and men, ſhould haue ſomething like God, and ſomething like men: leſt being in both like men, he ſhould bee too farre from God; or in both like God, he were too farre from men: and ſo were not a Mediatour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, wee are to conſider, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this Mediatour, two things. 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>His ſatisfaction.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II <hi>His interceſſion.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>His Satisfaction, was the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute diſcharge, and infinitely meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious performance, of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the Law requireth. He being obedient to the death, euen the curſed death of the Croſſe.</p>
               <p>His Interceſſion, is not a petition put vp to the Father, as we doe, and as he did in the dayes of his fleſh: <pb n="47" facs="tcp:8696:31"/> but, it is his appearing for euer, for vs, in the ſight of God, with the merit and worth of his obedience and bloudſhed: the which ſpeaketh better things, then 
<note n="o" place="margin">Heb. 22.24</note>
                  <hi>that of Abel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as Prayer moueth one, and preuaileth with him: ſo, the ſweet ſauour of Chriſt his ſacrifice and ſatisfaction, is euer in Gods no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, as the ſmell of a field which the Lord hath bleſſed.</p>
               <p>Anſwerably to theſe two, we are to conſider two things, in whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer we deſire at the Lords hands. 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>The right we haue to them.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>Our receiuing of them.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The Right wee haue to them, commeth by Chriſt his Sacrifice and Satisfaction. <hi>But now, in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle,<note n="p" place="margin">Ephe. 2.13.</note> 
                  <hi>yee who ſometimes were farre off, are made nigh by the bloud of Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Interceſſion reſpecteth the performance of the promiſes, and the perſonall beſtowing of thoſe good things. And, herein, he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth a double worke. I. Hee <pb n="48" facs="tcp:8696:32"/> prayeth for vs, Rom. 8.34. II. He prayeth with vs, perfecting and perfuming our praiers, that they may bee accepted of God his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and ſo, preſenteth them vnto him, Reuel. 8.3.4</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>§. 4.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Perſonall, referred to three heads. 3. To whom. and that, 1. God.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The Perſon to whom our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers muſt bee directed, followeth. Touching whom, we are to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der two things. 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>That God is our Obiect.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>How.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> God is the onely obiect of our prayers. <hi>Call vpon mee,</hi> ſaith hee, in the Pſalmes:<note n="q" place="margin">Pſ. 50.</note> And our Sauiour teacheth vs, in that his vniuerſall forme of prayer, to ſay, <hi>Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which art in heauen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that, by <hi>Father,</hi> he meaneth only God, doth euidently appeare, I. By things deſired, <hi>viz.</hi> the hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of his name, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of his Kingdome, &amp;c. II. By the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>For thine is the Kingdome, &amp;c.</hi> III. By his ſpeech to his Diſciples 
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:8696:32"/> elſewhere.<note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 23.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Call no man your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon the earth: for there is but one your Father, which is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi> This is his direction. And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe to pray, then Chriſt hath taught vs, is, (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>)<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ser. 6. <hi>De Orat. Dom. Aliter orare quàm docuit Chriſtus, non ignorantia ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la eſt, ſed &amp; culpa.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>not only an errour, but a fault.</hi> For the confirmation heereof, I will keepe me within the limits of this diſcourſe. The reaſons, then, are theſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>1</label> I. From the notation. God is onely to be prayed vnto: Becauſe, wee are onely liable to his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For what need I regard to ſue, for peace, to him, in whoſe danger I am not? or to appeale from him, who hath no power to proceed againſt mee? or to plead my pardon before him, who hath no authoritie to condemne, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit me. And as the Apoſtle wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth,<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>There is one that iudgeth me, the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>2</label> II. From the Principall Effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. Becauſe, it is the Spirit that helpeth our infirmities, teaching 
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8696:33"/> vs, yea praying for vs: whom to make a petitioner to Saints or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, or any creature, were horrible blaſphemy.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>3</label> III. From the Forme. Faiths apprehenſion and application be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Forme of Prayer, God is onely to be praied vnto: as hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, from whom wee haue the word of promiſe, the ground of faith: and who can ſearch our hearts, and ſee our faith. All the promiſes looke this way. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther promiſeth deliuerance,<note n="t" place="margin">Pſ. 50.</note> if wee call vpon him. The Sonne aſſures vs,<note n="n" place="margin">Ioh. 16.23.</note> that hee will doe, whatſoeuer we aske the Father. And the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> doth teſtifie vnto vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.15</note> we ſhall haue the requeſts we doe aske of him. And for the latter, The Lord doth appropriate to himſelfe, the ſearching of the heart:<note n="x" place="margin">Ier.
17.10.</note> 
                  <hi>I the Lord, ſearch the heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>4</label> IV. From the End. Prayer muſt be made onely to him, to whom ſo doing, God may be glorified, our dutie diſcharged, the promiſe come <pb n="51" facs="tcp:8696:33"/> in force, and ſuch meanes bee vſed, as the Lord hath appointed. All which are, when we pray to God: not one particular being otherwiſe attained vnto.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>5</label> V. From an inſeparable adiunct of Prayer. We muſt onely pray to him, to whom diuine adoration is due: wherein wee doe abaſe our ſelues, and exalt the Perſon to whom we pray. Now, that, both this doth inſeparably accompany prayer, appeareth in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Apoſtle deſcribeth prayer,<note n="y" place="margin">Epheſ. 3.14</note> onely by the outward geſture, whereby this ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is expreſſed. <hi>For this cauſe, I bow my knees,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>vnto the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> as alſo, that all diuine adoration is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to the Lord, may bee ſeene in the ſecond commaundement: where it is forbidden, ſo much as to bow down and worſhip any thing beſides the Lord. And thus the Church, in her purer times, did vſe this dutie. As, to content vs with one teſtimony, wee may ſee in the <pb n="52" facs="tcp:8696:34"/> Epiſtle written in the name of the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. hiſt. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi>
15.</note> touching the martyrdome of that renowned <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycarpus,</hi> mentioned by <hi>Euſebius.</hi>—<hi>Being ignorant</hi> (ſaith the Church, ſpeaking of their aduerſaries) <hi>that we can neuer forſake Chriſt, which died for the ſaluation of the whole world: that wee can worſhip none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For wee worſhip Chriſt as the Sonne of God, the Martyrs we loue as Diſciples and followers of the Lord, and that worthily, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible good loue they beare to their King and maſter, whoſe companions and diſciples we deſire to be.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>§. 5.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>3. To whom. and that, 2. His name, or God in his name.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The other point, is, how God is our Obiect: and that is, in his <hi>name.</hi> For, Prayer is a calling vpon the <hi>name of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I will take the cup of ſaluation,</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt<note n="z" place="margin">Pſ. 116.13.</note>) <hi>and call on the name of the Lord.</hi> And the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith,<note n="a" place="margin">Rom.
10.13</note> 
                  <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhall call on the name of the Lord, ſhal be ſaued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:8696:34"/>The <hi>name</hi> of God, is any ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant title, attributed to him, for our capacitie.</p>
               <p n="1">I. Then Prayer is not a confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed calling vpon God. But he that prayeth, muſt know how the Lord hath reuealed himſelfe, in the word: that ſo accordingly hee may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of him. <hi>How ſhall they call on him,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle,<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 10.14.</note> 
                  <hi>in whom they haue not beleeued? and how ſhall they beleeue in him, of whom they haue not heard?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">2.</note>II. In the ſecond place, wee muſt not onely know GOD, to whom wee pray, in ſome good meaſure: But, wee are alſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider thoſe proprieties in GOD, which doe the beſt ſort with our matter.</p>
               <p>As, if our ſpeech concerne the ſearching of our hearts, and the Lords knowing of our ſinnes, wee muſt conſider his <hi>omniſcience.</hi> If our miſery to be confeſſed, and how he might deale with vs: then wee are to conſider his <hi>iuſtice.</hi> If par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, 
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:8696:35"/> his mercie. If helpe, his power. If faith and hope, his vnchangeable veritie, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>An example hereof wee haue in <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 4 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Heare me calling, O God of my righteouſneſſe,</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>thou haſt ſet me at libertie, in a ſtraite, be gracious vnto mee, and heare my prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here the Pſalmiſt three wayes affected, conſidereth the Lord, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerably, in three proprieties. I. As an innocent, hee doth conſider the Lord as Patrone of Innocents, and innocent cauſes. <hi>Heare me calling, O God of my righteouſneſſe.</hi> II. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in miſerie and great diſtreſſe, he calleth to minde the gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of the Lord, confirmed by the experience of former deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. <hi>Thou haſt ſet me at libertie in a ſtraite.</hi> III. In the ſenſe of his frailties, from which none are free, and for which the Lord might iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reiect him, hee appealleth vnto mercie. <hi>Be gracious vnto mee, and heare my prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:8696:35"/>And thus doing, wee ſhall finde the <hi>relation</hi> betweene the proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in God, and their obiects in vs, a powerfull meanes to moue vs, touching humiliation, or conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>And thus much for the obiect of Prayer, to wit, <hi>God,</hi> and that in his name: that is, ſo conceiued and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon, as he hath pleaſed, for our direction and comfort, to make himſelfe knowne vnto vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>§. 6.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">How to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of God in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>Here, before we proceed, we will anſwere two Queſtions. The firſt whereof is this. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> How ſhould a man conceiue of God, in prayer?</p>
               <p>Thou muſt, touching thy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, note three things: 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>Thy preſenting thy ſelfe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>Thy Prayer.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. <hi>Thy actions and ieſtures.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> God is the obiect of all theſe: but in a diuers reſpect. God, in his Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and all-being, is the obiect of thy preſence: in his word and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, <pb n="56" facs="tcp:8696:36"/> is the obiect of thy prayer: and in heauen, is the obiect of thy actions and geſtures.</p>
               <p n="1">I. For the firſt, ſetting thy ſelfe to prayer, thou art to preſent thy ſelfe before the eſſence and all-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God, who filleth heauen and earth, and is beyond al heauens: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom thou art to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thy ſelfe to ſtand naked, thy moſt ſecret thoughts being mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in his ſight.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Touching thy Prayer, thou art to conſider how the Lord hath reuealed himſelfe in his word: as to be iuſt, mercifull, &amp;c. In regard of which, or any of which, as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne thee, being conſidered as in this al-being God, or God in them, thou art to be conuinced and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted accordingly.</p>
               <p n="3">III. And laſtly, thy geſtures, as kneeling, holding vp thy hands, &amp;c: thy actions of ſpeaking, ſighing, &amp;c: as alſo, thy humbling thy ſelfe in thy heart, and thy deſires of what thou wanteſt, &amp;c: are all to be dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted <pb n="57" facs="tcp:8696:36"/> towards heauen, not a repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of Gods eſſence: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, I. There ſitteth the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Chriſt, our Head and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour. II. Heauen is the Lords ſtore-houſe: and from thence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth euery good giuing, and euery perfect gift. III. And there the Lord reueales his glorie.</p>
               <p>The child ſitteth on the mothers knee, and looking her in the face, asketh beere, pointing with the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the glaſſe, or buttrie doore. I. The childe is with the mother: ſo wee preſent our ſelues before God, in his omni-preſence. II. The childe doth looke the mother in the face: euen ſo our ſpirituall eyes behold God, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> face of his Chriſt, as hee is manifeſted in the word. III. The childe maketh ſignes to the place, where that is, which hee would haue. So doe wee towards heauen.</p>
               <p>The Papiſt, becauſe hee would haue ſomthing ſenſibly before him, to kneele, looke and ſpeake to, hath <pb n="58" facs="tcp:8696:37"/> inuented Images, the worke of the craftſman, which haue eyes and ſee not, eares and heare not, neither ſpeake they through their throte.</p>
               <p>But the Lord hath prouided for vs a better obiect, euen <hi>God-in-Heauen.</hi> And, I. Whether ſhould the inſtinct of our renewed nature leade vs; but towards Heauen, where ſitteth our Lord and Head, in whom doth reſt our fulneſſe? II. Whether ſhould our affections draw vs; but to that place, where our inheritance lies, and our good things are laid vp? III. How can wee proſtrate our ſelues ſo fitly, as towards Heauen, where the Lord reuealeth that glorie, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the very Angels to couer their faces?</p>
               <p>Here we may take notice of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny defects, in prayer, and errours touching the conceiuing of God. I. Some place him onely in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Others, onely in the Church-top, Chamber, or place where they pray. II. Some but ſuppoſe God <pb n="59" facs="tcp:8696:37"/> to be before them: and ſo pray to a fained God. And ſo, whileſt they pray, they doe, indeed, but play, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, like Interluders, on a ſtage. III. Some acknowledging God his both preſence, and all-preſence, conceiue him of many faſhions.</p>
               <p>All which proceedeth, I. Partly, from our ignorance, being not rightlie inſtructed in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God. II. Partly, from our finitnes of capacitie, which muſt conſider one thing after another. And ſo, whiles we are buſied about one, we forget another. III. And partly, becauſe our nature cannot conceiue a thing to be, but concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it of ſome faſhion. For, in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall things, the forme giueth the being.<note place="margin">Forma dat eſſe.</note> Whence it commeth, that we are euer cloathing the <hi>Dietie,</hi> with ſome ſhape or other.</p>
               <p>Theſe things muſt be helped: I. By inſtruction, to learne aright. II. By Meditation afore-hand, to conceiue aright. III. By raiſing vp our ſelues, in prayer, from theſe <pb n="60" facs="tcp:8696:38"/> low earthly conceits, (ſo oft as they doe offer themſelues) to the true and right conſiderations ſpoken of before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>§. 7.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to God.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2</label> It may bee asked, in the ſecond place, How wee are to direct our prayers to God: whether to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Sonne, or holy Ghoſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I anſwere: The Lord is one God, in vnity, diſtinguiſhed in three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in Trinitie. And anſwerably all things that we do, are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>Simply, as an act.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>Respectiuely, in regard of the doing.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>As, to inſiſt vpon this dutie in hand, Our prayer ſimply reſpecteth God in vnitie: but, in regarde of putting it vp, the Trinitie.</p>
               <p>For, by the gracious aſſiſtance of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> through the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the welbeloued Sonne, wee exhibite our prayers to the eternall Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:8696:38"/>As in euery ordinarie petition put vp to a man, The petition ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply reſpecteth him to whom it is to be preſented. But in regard of the putting it vp, there muſt bee, I. A drawing. II. A preſenting. III. A receiuing.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe, in our prayers, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply we put them vp to God. But, for the manner, I. The <hi>Holie Ghoſt</hi> draweth them: teaching vs what to pray as we ſhould. <hi>Likewiſe</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle)<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> 
                  <hi>the Spirit alſo helpeth our infirmities: for wee know not what we ſhould pray for as we ought: but the ſpirit it ſelfe maketh inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for vs with gronings, which cannot be vttered.</hi> II. The Sonne doth perfect, perfume and preſent them. <hi>And another Angell</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iohn</hi>)<note n="e" place="margin">Reu.
8.3.</note> 
                  <hi>came and ſtood at the altar, hauing a golden cenſer, and there was giuen vnto him much incenſe, that he ſhould offer it with the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of all Saints, vpon the golden al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar which was before the throne.</hi> III. The Father doth receiue them. <pb n="62" facs="tcp:8696:39"/> 
                  <hi>And the ſmoake of the incenſe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iohn</hi>)<note n="f" place="margin">Reu. 8.4.</note> 
                  <hi>which came with the prayers of the Saints, aſcended vp before God, out of the Angels hand.</hi> And thus much for an anſwer to the firſt part of the Queſtion.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond place, we may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our prayers to any Perſon in the Trinitie. I. To the Father: as to the Epheſians,<note n="g" place="margin">Epheſ. 3.14 15.</note> 
                  <hi>For this cauſe</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>I bow my knees vnto the father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> II. To the Sonne: as to <hi>Timothie,</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">2. Tim. 4.22</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord Ieſus Chriſt be with thy ſpirit, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Steuen</hi> cried,<note n="i" place="margin">Act.
7.59,</note> 
                  <hi>Lord Ieſus receiue my ſpirit.</hi> III. To the Holy Ghoſt: as to the Romanes,<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 15.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Now, the God of patience and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, grant you to be like minded, &amp;c.</hi> Yet not excluſiuely, but inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely: in any one vnderſtanding al. For, euery of their working doth argue one anothers manner, in the Trinitie, and all one matter, in the vnitie.</p>
               <p>Touching which, we may conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der three things further. 
<list>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:8696:39"/>
                     <item>I. <hi>When we alter.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>How farre.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. <hi>Wherefore.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>For the firſt, we are to know, that the three Perſons are diſtinguiſhed in their proprieties, and manner of working: as alſo, that theſe three generall Effects, (Creation, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and Regeneration) are attributed (though incluſiuely, yet) diſtinctlie to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> three Perſons: Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the Father: Redemption, to the Son: Regeneration, to the Holy Ghoſt. As we may ſee in the Creed.</p>
               <p>Now, as our matter doth alter, in any of theſe regards, ſo may we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our obiect.</p>
               <p>For the ſecond, namely, how farre we alter. We muſt conſider that, in regard of, 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>Our obiect.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>Our Prayers.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. <hi>Our ſelues.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>In regard of the Obiect, <hi>God,</hi> our altring is Perſonal, not Eſſential. For there is but one indiuiſible God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:8696:40"/>In regard of our Prayer, our al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring doth not reſpect the prayer ſimply: but reſpectiuely, as a prayer containing ſuch or ſuch matter.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, in regard of our ſelues, we vary our phraſe, not our faith. We direct our prayer, or ſpeech in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to this or that Perſon: but, our faith is one and the ſame, grounded vpon the promiſes, made to vs, by that one indiuiſible Deitie, equally reſpecting each Perſon in the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</p>
               <p>In the laſt place, the reaſons why wee alter our obiect, that is, direct our ſpeech in prayer, to this or that Perſon, are, I. To conforme our prayers and termes, to the Trinities diſtinct manner of working. II. To ſtirre vp, in vs, a greater reuerent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of euery Perſon, as God. The which our Sauiour ſheweth to be a ſpecial reaſon of their diſtinct man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of working.<note n="l" place="margin">Ioh. 5.22.23.</note> 
                  <hi>The Father</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>iudgeth no man: but hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted all iudgement to the Sonne: that men might honour the Sonne, as <pb n="65" facs="tcp:8696:40"/> they honour the Father.</hi> III. The better to ſtirre vp and ſtrengthen our Faith. And that by mentioning the very diſtinct Efficients, and workers of the good things we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. As alſo, to moue affection, in thankeſ-giuing. Hauing, ſo, the more libertie to vſe the termes, that doe concerne their incommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble proprieties.</p>
               <p>Yet, vſually we direct our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers onely to the Father. Becauſe, by office, I. He is the fountaine of all goodneſſe. II. He is Firſt-willer. III. It belongeth to him, to receiue our prayers.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. V.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Adiuncts</hi> of Prayer fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. And they are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, as concerning it, 
<list>
                  <item>I. Simply.</item>
                  <item>II. Reſpectiuely.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <argument>
                  <p>The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuncts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, 1. Simply.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The Adiuncts of prayer, ſimply conſidered, are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">I. That prayer is a dutie belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="66" facs="tcp:8696:41"/> to euery man. As appeareth in that, it is commanded in the moral, and a generall rule is preſcribed, by our Sauiour in the Goſpell.</p>
               <p n="2">II. It is a dutie to which the Lord hath pleaſed, to <hi>tye</hi> moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſes; as,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſ.
50.</note> 
                  <hi>Call vpon me, in the euill day, ſo will I deliuer thee. Aske,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour,<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 16.24.</note> 
                  <hi>and yee ſhall receiue.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Iames,</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Iam. 4.2.</note> layeth the cauſe of want, vpon the neglect of this dutie.</p>
               <p n="3">III. It hath goodly <hi>immunities.</hi> No place, no time, no perſon, no thing) ſo far as God may be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and wee haue good) can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe againſt it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Daniel</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 6.10.22</note> in his Chamber, and in the denne: <hi>Dauid</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Pſ.
55.17.</note> morning, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and at noone day: they both called vpon the Lord, and he heard them.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Craft</hi> of <hi>Achitophel,</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">2. Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 15.31</note> The power of <hi>Senacherib,</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 37.16. &amp;c.</note> the walls of Iericho,<note n="h" place="margin">Ioſh. 6.20.</note> The waters of the red ſea,<note n="i" place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> The Clouds,<note n="k" place="margin">Iam.
5.17.</note> nay the Sun and Moone<note n="l" place="margin">Ioſh.
10.12.</note> could no waies infringe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:8696:41"/>It raiſeth fruit out of the earth:<note n="m" place="margin">Iam. 5.18.</note> and pulleth grace downe from<note n="n" place="margin">Iam. 1.5.</note> heauen.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. The Profit is vnſpeakable. Yet, to inſiſt vpon ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars: Beſides what may be gathered from the former properties, it is a faithfull ſeruant, it will neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue vs. It is a ſure meſſenger, it cannot bee intercepted, but goeth to heauen inuiſible. It is a ſwift Poſt, if we be brought into a ſtrait, it is with God in a moment. In a word, it is our only meanes, of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which wee haue to the Lord, both in proſperitie and aduerſitie.</p>
               <p n="5">V. The Power is irreſiſtable. For what ſaith the Apoſtle<note n="o" place="margin">Heb. 11.33.34.</note> of <hi>Faith,</hi> which may not bee likewiſe ſaid of Prayer? For by it haue the worthies of God, ſubdued King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, wrought righteouſneſſe, obtained promiſes, ſtopped the mouthes of Lions, quenched the violence of fire, eſcaped the edge of the ſword, out of weakeneſſe were made ſtrong, waxed valiant 
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:8696:42"/> in fight, turned to flight the armies of the aliens. To be ſhort, it is the Chariot and Horſemen of Iſraell.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. Laſtly, It is ſo worthy, ſo eſſentiall a fruit of religion, and of ſuch generall vſe, that it is oft put for all religion. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is the Temple<note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 27.13</note> called the <hi>houſe of prayer.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. 2.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuncts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, II. Attributed to it in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of, 1. The Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon praying, and 1. His conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 2. His perſon, and 1. Soule. 2. Body. 3. Both.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The <hi>Adiuncts</hi> of Prayer, in the ſecond place, are ſuch as are attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to it, in reſpect of, 
<list>
                     <item>I. The Perſon praying.</item>
                     <item>II. The Ends of prayer.</item>
                     <item>III. The Subiect.</item>
                     <item>IV. The Time.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Thoſe attributed to it, in reſpect of the perſon praying, doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, 
<list>
                     <item>I. Either his Condition.</item>
                     <item>II. Or his Perſon.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Touching the ſtate and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the perſon praying, It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired alwaies in ſuch prayers as a man looketh to finde comfort in, <pb n="69" facs="tcp:8696:42"/> that they be the prayers.</p>
               <p n="1">I. Of a man that is regenerate. 
<note n="q" place="margin">Gen. 4.</note>For the Lord reiected the offering of <hi>Cain,</hi> becauſe hee had a quarrell with his perſon. And the Spirit, who helpeth our infirmities, and teacheth vs to pray as we ought, is ſaid<note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 8.26.27.</note> to make <hi>interceſſion for the Saints:</hi> that is, <hi>onely</hi> for the Saints.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Of a man repentant, for his euils which from time to time doe eſcape him; as wee may ſee in the propheſie of <hi>Ieremy,</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">Ier. 14.10.11.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Thus
(ſaith the Lord) vnto his people, thus haue they loued to wander, they haue not refrained their feet, therefore the Lord doth not accept them, hee will now remember their iniquitie, and viſit their ſinnes. Then ſaid the Lord vnto mee, pray not for this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for their good. When they faſt, I will not heare their cry, and when they offer burnt offering, and an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, I will not accept them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. Of a diligent and dutifull hearer of the Word of GOD. 
<note n="t" place="margin">Ier. 11.9.10.11.</note>
                  <hi>And the Lord ſaid vnto mee,</hi> ſaith <pb n="70" facs="tcp:8696:43"/> 
                  <hi>Ieremy, A conſpiracy is found among the men of Iudah, and among the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of Ieruſalem. They are turned backe to the iniquities of their forefathers, which refuſed to heare my words, &amp;c.—Therefore, (thus ſaith the Lord) Behold, I will bring euill vpon them, which they ſhall not be able to eſcape; &amp; though they ſhall cry vnto mee, I will not hearken vnto them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. Of one that is charitable, 
<note n="u" place="margin">Mar. 11.25.</note>
                  <hi>And when yee ſtand praying,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour, <hi>forgiue, if yee haue ought againſt any: that your Father alſo which is in heauen, may forgiue you your treſpaſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The <hi>Adiuncts</hi> of prayer, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the perſon of him that praieth, doe concerne. 
<list>
                     <item>1. Soule.</item>
                     <item>2. Body.</item>
                     <item>3. Or both.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Touching the ſoule, it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that, in regard of,</p>
               <p n="1">I. The vnderſtanding, our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers be</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:8696:43"/>1. Of knowledge. Our Sauiour<note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 20.22.</note> telleth the ſonnes of <hi>Zebedee,</hi> by way of reproofe, that they asked they knew not what.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of conſcience, in ſubmiſſion to Gods command. 
<note n="x" place="margin">Iſa. 1.12.</note>
                  <hi>When ye come to appear before me,</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>who hath required this at your hand, to treade my courts.</hi> The Lord did require their appearance, but not ſuch an appearing: they came, but not right: they came for cuſtome, and not for conſcience. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord had no pleaſure in them.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The will: that there bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, in our prayers,</p>
               <p n="1">1. A ſubmiſſion of our wills to Gods will. 
<note n="y" place="margin">Mat. 26.39</note>Heereof wee haue a worthy example in our Sauiour, <hi>O my Father,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>if it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, let this cup paſſe from me: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, not as I will, but as thou wilt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. A reſigning vp our ſelues to reſt vpon God. 
<note n="z" place="margin">Ier. 14.22.</note>
                  <hi>Are there any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the vanities of the Gentiles,</hi> 
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:8696:44"/> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>that can cauſe raine? or can the heauens giue ſhowers? Art thou not hee, O Lord, our God? therefore we will waite vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee: for thou haſt made all theſe things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. The affections. There muſt be, 
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Feeling.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Feruency.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Sighes and groanes.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The <hi>Adiuncts,</hi> which doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne prayer, in reſpect of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, are the geſtures fitting and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to be vſed.</p>
               <p>The which are indifferent. Yet God is the God of order: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all things are to bee done de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently and in order.</p>
               <p>Theſe then are vſually obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Caſting downe the eyes, in confeſſion of ſinne and iudgement, in ſigne of confuſion. Thus, our Sauiour ſaith, that the Publicane ſtanding a farre off, would not lift vp ſo much as his eyes to heauen: <pb n="73" facs="tcp:8696:44"/> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Luk. 18.13.</note>but ſmoate vpon his breaſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Looking vp towards Heauen, in petition, in ſigne of hope, as alſo, in thankſ-giuing. By this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture the Pſalmiſt deſcribeth pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er it ſelfe.<note n="b" place="margin">Pſ. 123.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Vnto thee lift I vppe mine eyes: O thou that dwelleſt in the heauens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Holding vp the hands, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by that exhortation of <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my;</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Lam. 3.41.</note> 
                  <hi>Let vs lift vp,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>our heart with our hands vnto God in the heauens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The <hi>Adiunct,</hi> which concerneth both ſoule and body, is <hi>Adoration:</hi> conſiſting in a deuout humbling our ſelues before the high and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Maieſtie of our God, in our hearts: expreſſed by an anſwerable carriage of the body, which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially kneeling, if conueniently we can.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§. 3.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>II. The Ends of prayer. III. The ſubiect, and 1. Verball. 2. Reall. 3. Perſonall.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The <hi>Adiuncts</hi> of Prayer, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the ends of prayer, are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the ends handled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. <pb n="74" facs="tcp:8696:45"/> 
I will note onely three.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <list>
                     <item n="1">
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Prayer is an appeale from the condemning ſentence of the Law, to the mercifull promiſes of the <hi>Goſpell.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item n="2">
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. It is a letter of Atturney, from Ieſus Chriſt, to receiue of God the Father, the good things which God hath promiſed, and Chriſt purchaſed.</item>
                     <item n="3">
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. It is our Cart and carriage to bring home our heauenly Harueſt, ſowen, for vs, at Chriſts incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ripened during his obedience to the death, reaped at his aſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and daily made fit for carriage, by his interceſſion. And whiles we haue any croppe abroad, that is, whiles we are heere, and haue our bleſſings in heauen, wee may not ſet vp our carriages: but as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle exhorteth, muſt <hi>pray conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually.</hi> But more of that hereafter.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> The <hi>Adiuncts,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>ſubiect,</hi> and,</p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>Verball,</hi> are theſe: Our words muſt not be,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:8696:45"/>1. Affected, but plaine. We vſe not words and termes for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but to expreſſe our mindes, and lay open our deſires. If, then they bee coyned and curious, and nothing or little to the purpoſe, they are idle; and to vſe the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles words,<note n="d" place="margin">1. Cor. 14.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Thy ſpirit prayeth, but thy vnderſtanding is vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, if thy words be plaine, and thy termes ordinary, and yet ſuit with thy minde, they are profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and to great good purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What profiteth a golden key, if it cannot open what wee would haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened? or what hurteth a wooden key, if it can doe this? ſeeing we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire nothing, but to open that which is ſhut,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. de doctri. Chriſt. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. <hi>Quid prodeſt clauis aurea, ſi aperire quod volumus non poteſt? aut quid obeſt lignea, ſi hoc poteſt? qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do nihil quari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, niſi a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perire, quod clauſum erat.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Vaine and idle: but pertinent and to the purpoſe. <hi>When we pray,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour,<note n="f" place="margin">Mat.
6.7.</note> 
                  <hi>vſe not vaine repetitions as the heathen doe: for they thinke that they ſhall bee heard for their much ſpeaking.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. In a ſtrange tongue, but <pb n="76" facs="tcp:8696:46"/> knowne and familiar. <hi>The Greeks,</hi> ſaith <hi>Origen,</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Orig. contr. Celſum, lib.</hi> 8. <hi>Graeci quidem gracè Deum nominant, &amp; Latine Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, &amp; ſinguli item natiua &amp; vernacula lingua Deum preca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>name God in Greeke, and the Latines in Latine, and all pray to God, and praiſe him in their natiue and mother tongue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> Here it may bee asked, whether it be lawfull to pray in any but our natiue tongue?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I anſwere: Among the ignorant and vnlearned, where they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by dutie, and their edification is to be aymed at: it is not warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, by the Word of God, to pray in any other, but our mother tongue. For, how ſhall he, as the Apoſtle ſaith,<note n="h" place="margin">1. Cor. 14.16</note> 
                  <hi>that occupieth the roome of the vnlearned ſay, Amen, at thy giuing of thankes, ſeeing hee vnderſtandeth not what thou ſayeſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in exerciſes of Scholer-ſhip, and in priuate, (prouided a man vnderſtand what himſelfe ſaith) it is not vnlawfull. <hi>For he that is the Lord of all tongues,</hi> ſaith <hi>Origen,</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Orig. cont. Celſ. lib.</hi> 8. <hi>Ille enim qui eſt linguarum omnium Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus, audit quaeuis lingua orantes, id<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> non ſecùs, quàm ſi vna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vocem excipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret è variis linguis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſam. Deus enim cùm praeſit machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae vniuerſi, non eſt quaſi vnus aliquit, qui linguam vel graecam vel Barbaram ſit ſortitus, vt caeteras neſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>heareth them that pray in any tongue, as if hee ſhould heare one voyce pronounced from diuers <pb n="77" facs="tcp:8696:46"/> tongues. For God, ſeeing he ruleth the whole world, is not as ſome one, that hath gotten the Greeke or La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine tongue ſo as he knoweth none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet in priuate where men haue libertie, it is not good to abuſe it, to the hinderance of the gracious worke of Gods holy Spirit, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to vſe that language, in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, whereby the minde may be the leaſt diſtracted, and the affections moſt inflamed.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> II. <hi>Reall,</hi> Touching the things deſired in prayer,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Our prayers muſt alwayes be for good things. And that, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of both the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, the meanes and manner of comming by them, as alſo our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of vſing them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Temporal bleſſings, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſpirituall, with the ſpeciall meanes and circumſtances of all, muſt moderately be referred to the Lord, and to his wiſedome.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The more worthy the things <pb n="78" facs="tcp:8696:47"/> are, the more inſtant wee may and muſt be for them.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> III. <hi>Perſonal.</hi> Touching which, this is an inſeparable <hi>Adiunct</hi> of praier vnder the Goſpell, that it muſt alwayes be put vp, to God, in and by the Mediation of another, <hi>viz, Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>§. 4.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>IV. The time: conſidered in reſpect, 1. Of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie: and that in reſpect of 1. The action of prayer. 2. The occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and 1. Ordinary-continued. 2. Now &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>Laſtly, <hi>To euery thing,</hi> ſaith <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.1.</note> 
                  <hi>is a ſeaſon, and a time to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery purpoſe vnder the heauen.</hi> And ſo to prayer, then. Concerning which wee are to conſider two things. 
<list>
                     <item>I. The Opportunitie for praier.</item>
                     <item>II. The Continuance of it.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For the firſt: all times, as times, may ſerue for prayer. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> I. Time is beſtowed on vs for the glory of God. II. The Lord is vnchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, the ſame at all times.</p>
               <p>It cannot be ſaid of him, as <hi>Elias</hi> ſaid of <hi>Baal,</hi> that he is talking, or purſuing his enemies, &amp;c, or that any action, or accident can hinder him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:8696:47"/>For hee ſeeth and knoweth all things <hi>together, at once, alwayes:</hi>
                  <hi>Simul, ſemel, ſemper.</hi> neither doth he that keepeth Iſrael, euer ſlumber or ſleepe.</p>
               <p>But if wee looke to the dutie, the time is to bee conſidered in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of, 
<list>
                     <item>I. The action.</item>
                     <item>II. The occaſion.</item>
                  </list> of prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For the <hi>action,</hi> It being a calling vpon the name of God, the time muſt be free, (I ſpeake of ſet pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers now) from worldly buſineſſe. Otherwiſe, the minde muſt needes bee incombred, and the body can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not performe duties requiſite.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The occaſion of prayer is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold: 
<list>
                     <item>I. Ordinary-continued.</item>
                     <item>II. Now and then.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The Ordinary-continued occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of prayer, is,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Either concerning the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like worſhip of God, to wit, from Sabaoth to Sabaoth, principally, or other-whiles.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or in regard of the generall <pb n="80" facs="tcp:8696:48"/> courſes of things, in our ſeuerall places. Concerning which (as I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it) <hi>Daniel</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Dan. 6.10.</note> prayed three times a day: and <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith,<note n="m" place="margin">Pſ. 55.17.</note> In the morning, and euening, and at noone day, will I praiſe thee.</p>
               <p>Eſpecially, morning and euen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, it ſhould not be omitted. For which cauſe prayer is called, of ſome, <hi>the key of the day, and the bolt of the night:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Clauis dici, ſera noctis.</hi>
                  </note> that is, The holy meanes whereby, a comfortable paſſage is made, to a bleſſed and proſperous day following: and the onely ſtop-gap to preuent iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and keepe forth croſſes, for the delightfull inioying of ſafetie and quiet, in the night ſeaſon.</p>
               <p>For examples, conſider theſe two. When <hi>Iacob</hi> had ſeene the viſion at <hi>Bethel,</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Gen.
28.18.19.20.21.22.</note> as hee was going to ſeeke for his ſafetie: riſing vp early in the morning, he firſt ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his thankefulneſſe, ſetting apart that place to the ſeruice of that God, that had appeared vnto him: <hi>He took the ſtone,</hi> ſaith the text, <hi>that 
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:8696:48"/> he had put for his pillowes, and ſet it vp for a pillar, and powred oyle vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the top of it.</hi> Hauing done this, he calleth vpon the name of the Lord, for a bleſſing, for the time follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>And Iacob vowed a vow, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, If God will be with me, and will keepe me in this way that I goe, and will giue me bread to eat, and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to put on, ſo that I come againe to my fathers houſe in peace: then ſhall the Lord be my God, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other, is the practiſe of the Iſraelites,<note n="o" place="margin">Exod. 11.7 Ch. 12.29.30</note> the night in which the Lord deſtroyed the Firſt-borne in Egypt. The Egyptians goe car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to bed, they call not vpon the Lord, they regard not the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of Iſrael: But the Iſraelites eat the Paſſeouer, and beſprinkle the poſts of their houſes with the bloud of the Lambe.</p>
               <p>Now, what was the ſucceſſe? At mid-night the Lord ſmote all the firſt-borne in the land of Egypt, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt-borne of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> that ſate on his throne, vnto the firſt-borne 
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:8696:49"/> of the captiue that was in the dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, and all the firſt-bred of cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell.—And there was a great cry in Egypt: for there was not a houſe where there was not one dead. But againſt any of the children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, did not a dogge mooue his tongue, againſt man or beaſt. Thus much for the ordinary-continued occaſion of prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> To returne now from whence I haue ſomewhat digreſſed: The oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions now and then, are in reſpect of the ſeuerall obiects, which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelues in our courſes, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ariſing in our hearts, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents continually falling out in our liues. Thus <hi>Dauid</hi> praiſed God,<note n="p" place="margin">Pſ. 119.164</note> 
                  <hi>ſeuen times a day:</hi> that is, many times, euen ſo oft as occaſion was offered.</p>
               <p>This is done by <hi>eiaculations,</hi> that is, ſhort ſententious ſpeeches, or liftings vp of the heart to the Lord. Hitherto of the opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:8696:49"/>
               <head>§. 5.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>II. Of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>Touching the continuance of prayer, wee are to conſider two things: 
<list>
                     <item>I. How oft wee muſt pray to God.</item>
                     <item>II. How long.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>For the Firſt, wee are to pray ſo oft as occaſion is offered: <hi>pray con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle,<note n="q" place="margin">1. The. 5.17</note> wee are to omit no opportunity; but to take all occaſions: yea, we ſhould ſeeke occaſions to haue an errand to God. Poore children will make many errands, and bee glad to bee ſent to a houſe where they fare well. And where fare we ſo well, as at Gods houſe?</p>
               <p>The other point propounded, is, how long we are to continue pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And that is to be conſidered in reſpect of, 
<list>
                     <item>1. Prayer.</item>
                     <item>2. The thing prayed for.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>For the Firſt, we are to continue our action of praying, ſo long as <pb n="84" facs="tcp:8696:50"/> matter is afforded, and wee can keepe our mindes and affections, in ſuch temper, as becommeth that heauenly dutie. Prouided alwayes,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That when wee are praying alone, we forget not the call of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſions. Remembring, as I alleaged afore out of Eccleſiaſtes, that <hi>to euery thing there is a ſeaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That when others ioyne with vs, we haue reſpect of their imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as the time requireth, and of their weakeneſſe, at all times.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, touching the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of our prayers, in reſpect of the things prayed for, wee are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted by our Sauiour,<note n="r" place="margin">Luke 18.1.2. &amp;c.</note> to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and to perſeuere: after the example of the woman, who, by her importunitie, preuailed with the careleſſe Iudge.</p>
               <p>This continuance is by ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but not without intermiſſion.</p>
               <p>Againe, this ſucceſſion is not only of ſet-praiers: but euen when wee are about other exerciſes, wee are to ſend forth <hi>eiaculations,</hi> with <pb n="85" facs="tcp:8696:50"/> ſighs and groanes, till the Lord pleaſe to make his good wil known vnto vs.</p>
               <p>And this wee are, eſpecially to doe, when the things we deſire, or (in the caſe of thankſ-giuing) the things we haue receiued, come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our mindes. <hi>I thanke my God,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle to the Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Phil. 1.3.</note> 
                  <hi>vpon euery remembrance of you.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
            <p>WE come now to the diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of prayer. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are to conſider, 
<list>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">The parts.</note>
                     <note place="margin">1.</note>I. The <hi>Parts.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">2.</note>II. The <hi>Kindes.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> of <hi>Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <argument>
                  <p>The diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution, and, into The parts.  1. Confeſſion. The which confeſſion muſt be free.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The Parts of prayer are two. 
<list>
                     <item n="1">I. <hi>Confeſſion.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item n="2">II. A dealing with God, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the things confeſſed.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Confeſſion is a free acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement to the Lord: either how wee doe conceiue of his glorious <pb n="86" facs="tcp:8696:51"/> Maieſtie: or, how the caſe is with vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, we doe confeſſe, how wee doe conceiue of the Lord. <hi>O Lord of boaſts,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hezekiah,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Eſa. 37.16.</note> 
                  <hi>God of Iſrael, that dwelleſt betweene the Cherubims, thou art the God, euen thou alone, of all the Kingdomes of the earth, thou haſt made heauen and earth ſo, Gen.</hi> 32.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.6.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In the ſecond place we doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe how the caſe is with vs. And this conſiſteth in the confeſſion,</p>
               <p n="1">I. Of our wants: <hi>viz.</hi> I. Sinne: as <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Pſ. 51.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Againſt thee, thee only haue I ſinned.</hi> II. The inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; troubles ariſing from ſin. As the ſame <hi>Dauid,</hi> elſe-where,<note n="c" place="margin">Pſ. 6.2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Haue mercy vpon mee, O Lord, for I am weake; O Lord, heale me, for my bones are vexed: my ſoule is alſo ſore vexed.</hi> And againe,<note n="d" place="margin">Pſ. 25.16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Turne thee vnto me, and haue mercy vpon me: for I am deſolate and afflicted. The troubles of my heart are inlarged.</hi> III. How ſhort wee are of what the Lord requireth of vs. <hi>Behold,</hi> 
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:8696:51"/> ſaith the Pſalmiſt,<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 51.5.6.7.</note> 
                  <hi>I was ſhapen in iniquitie: and in ſinne did my mother conceiue mee. Behold thou deſireſt truth in the inward parts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. Of Gods goodneſſe: conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as, I. beſtowed on vs, II. or promiſed to vs. And both, in, I. ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things. As in that thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of our Sauiour:<note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 10.21.</note> 
                  <hi>I thanke thee O father of heauen and earth, that thou hast hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and hast reuealed them vnto babes: euen ſo father, for ſo it ſeemed good in thy ſight.</hi> 2. Or in temporall things: as <hi>Iacob,</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 32.10</note> 
                  <hi>I am not worthy of the leaſt of all the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and of all the truth, which thou haſt ſhewed vnto thy ſeruant: for with my ſtaffe I paſſed ouer this Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and now I am become two bands.</hi> 
This our Confeſſion, as I ſaid, muſt be free: namely,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I. In our confeſſion of the Lord, ſhewing, 
<list>
                     <item>1. A heart diſclaiming all other helpes, as vaine.</item>
                     <item>2. A reſolute ſetting-vp of the <pb n="88" facs="tcp:8696:52"/> Lord to bee our God, ſole and all-ſufficient.</item>
                     <item>3. A comfortable conceit of his gracious diſpoſition towards vs, in his Chriſt. Wherefore we will not hide from our God, how the caſe is with vs.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> II. In our confeſſion of our wants, ſhewing, 
<list>
                     <item>1. Our vnfained hatred of ſinne: which we will in no-wiſe conceale.</item>
                     <item>2. Our loue of good things: for which cauſe wee will acknowledge our defects.</item>
                     <item>3. Our zeale of Gods glorie: euerie way exalting him, by all meanes debaſing our ſelues.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> III. In our confeſſion of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies receiued, ſhewing, 
<list>
                     <item>1. An acknowledgement of our vnworthineſſe, to haue the leaſt of them.</item>
                     <item>2. Inabilitie to get them: were not our good God ſo bounteous and free-hearted toward vs.</item>
                     <item>3. The great neede wee haue of them: and conſequently the excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <pb n="89" facs="tcp:8696:52"/> benefit and ſweete, that wee haue found by them.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Inſomuch, that our ſoules are fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, by reaſon of them, 
<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 63.5.</note>
                  <hi>as with marrow and fatnes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. 2.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>II. The ſecond part of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: which conſiſteth in, I. Petition. 1. Supplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 2. Precation. 3. Interceſſion. How inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion is vſed, in that, 1. to Tim. the 2.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The other part is a <hi>dealing with God,</hi> concerning the things confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, in the two latter places. And that by way of, 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>Petition.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>Thankeſgiuing.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <note place="margin">Theſe ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accepted are kinds of prayer, and not parts: Supplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Petition, and Interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall praiers: but we vſing them ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I ſo call them.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt is agreeable to our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our wants. The other, to the confeſſion of good things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued.</p>
               <p>The acknowledgement of God, in the firſt place, what he is in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to vs, is the propounding of God, and placing him as our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect: and the ground of our dealing with him, in both theſe caſes: I meane, both in petition, &amp; thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing. Let vs come to the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> 
                  <hi>Petition,</hi> is a calling vpon the <pb n="90" facs="tcp:8696:53"/> name of God, as a Father: deſiring reliefe, in reſpect of our wants. And it is ſubdiuided, by the Apoſtle, to <hi>Timothie,</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.1.</note> into three branches, 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>Supplication.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>Precation</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Called alſo Prayers, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>.</item>
                     <item>III. <hi>Interceſſion.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>Supplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> is an humble requeſt vnto God, for remiſſion and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, vpon the conſcience of that ſtate wherein we ſtand, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>Precation,</hi> is a ſuite exhibited to the Lord, for his good bleſſings and fauours, concerning both ſoule and body.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>Interceſſion,</hi> is vſually taken for a requeſt put vp for others. And ſo, indeed, it is ordinarily vſed in the Scriptures. But it ſeemeth to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe taken here.</p>
               <p>My reaſon is, becauſe that if this be the proper acception of it, in this place, giuing it the difference from <hi>ſupplication,</hi> and <hi>precation:</hi> then they two are to be performed for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, reſpecting onely euery mans <pb n="91" facs="tcp:8696:53"/> owne particular.</p>
               <p>But the Apoſtle commandeth, that ſupplication and precation be performed for others alſo: In a word, hee willeth that all the foure duties be performed for all men.</p>
               <p>Againe, Interceſſion ſeemeth to bee taken heere, for ſuch a dutie as may bee performed of a man for himſelfe. For the Apoſtle doth not here command the duties ſimply: but he inlargeth them, in reſpect of the obiect: willing that they ſhould performe them, not only for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and ſome few others, to wit, beleeuers: but that withall, they ought to remember all men, and, as Perſons of moſt ſpeciall reſpect, Kings and all that are in authoritie.</p>
               <p>To ſhew briefly, then, what I thinke. I take it to be a dutie, to be performed, in the caſe of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and corrections.</p>
               <p>For Interceſſion is a comming betweene, as partie, and partie, ſo part and part. As, to interrupt a man in his ſpeech, is interceſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:8696:54"/>And onely in the caſe of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wee labour to interrupt the Lord, ſtepping, with our repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance and humble inuocation, betweene his threatnings &amp; the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or betweene the deſert of ſin iuſtly prouoking him, and the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: or when hee hath entred into iudgement with vs, by holy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpellation, betweene the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and conſummation of his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, thereby labouring to breake off the courſe of thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</p>
               <p>And the Apoſtles method ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to fauour this expoſition. For hee ſetteth ſupplication in the firſt place, which is a dealing with the Lord, in the caſe of forgiuenes, &amp;c. Then precation, whereby we deſire bleſſings, whereof daily and houre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wee haue neede. And, in the laſt place, interceſſion, whereby wee deale with the Lord, but now and then. The which is in the caſe of iudgement, when the Lord pleaſeth to correct.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:8696:54"/>
               <head>§. 3.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> II. Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. The vſe of thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. Reaſons to moue vs to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> The other branch, in generall, to be conſidered, is <hi>thankeſgiuing:</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Apoſtle, in that former place to <hi>Timothie.</hi> And that it is a part of prayer, (howſoeuer many make it a diſtinct thing from pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) as appeareth both in the new Teſtament and the old.</p>
               <p>In the old, in that ſong of <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah,</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">1. Sam. 2.1.</note> where it is ſaid, that ſhe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and yet, as is plaine to be ſeene, it was a ſong of thankſgiuing.<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>And Hannah prayed, and ſaid, My heart reioyceth in the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> In the new: as in the 1. Cor. 14.14,15,16.17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thankeſgiuing,</hi> is a calling vpon the name of God, as a Father, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him for his good mercies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed, or promiſed.</p>
               <p>Vnto the performance of which dutie, <hi>Dauid</hi> inciteth his ſoule:<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 103.1.2.</note> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Bleſſe the Lord, O my ſoule: and all that is within me, bleſſe his holie name. Bleſſe the Lord, O my ſoule: <pb n="94" facs="tcp:8696:55"/> and forget not all his benefits.</hi> So likewiſe, Pſal. 107.1,2,8.15.21.31. Where he doth not only exhort to the dutie: but alſo, foure times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile the neglect of it: in theſe words, <hi>O that men would praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe: and for his wonderfull workes to the children of men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This dutie muſt bee renewed, as the Lord pleaſeth to renew his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. As we haue a worthie example in <hi>Dauid:</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 40.3.</note> 
                  <hi>He hath put a new ſong in my mouth,</hi> euen <hi>praiſe vnto our God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if new faile, old bleſſings may neuer be forgotten. Therefore, <hi>Dauid</hi> (though the children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael had praiſed the Lord, long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for his wonders in Egypt: and though they were long before his time, yet) compoſeth a Pſalme<note n="n" place="margin">Pſal.
105.</note> of thankſgiuing for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Againe, not onely perſonall and particular bleſſings: but alſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and publike, binde vs to bee thankfull. When the foundation of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:8696:55"/> the Temple of the Lord was laid,<note n="o" place="margin">Eſra. 3.11.</note> they praiſed the Lord: <hi>and all the people</hi> (ſaith the text) <hi>ſhouted with a great ſhoute, when they praiſed the Lord.</hi> Yea, not onely for extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie: but we muſt be thankfull for ordinarie mercies, as our liuing, our mouing and our being: For euen theſe, as the Apoſtle witneſſeth,<note n="p" place="margin">Act.
17.28.</note> wee haue not of our ſelues, but of God.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, we muſt be thankfull, not onely in priuate: but likewiſe in publike. <hi>I will praiſe the Lord</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt)<note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 111.1.</note> 
                  <hi>with my whole heart: in the aſſembly of the vpright, and in the congregation.</hi> So Pſal. 66.16.</p>
               <p>To the performance of which worthie dutie, (I meane <hi>thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing</hi>) theſe Reaſons may moue vs.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I. It is a moſt ſpeciall meanes of glorifying the Lord. <hi>Who ſo offreth praiſe,</hi> (ſaith he)<note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 50.23.</note> 
                  <hi>glorifieth me.</hi> It is the Lords freehold, and his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt portion. <hi>Thou art holy,</hi>
(ſaith the Pſalmiſt)<hi rend="sup">ſ</hi> 
                  <hi>O thou that inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the praiſes of Iſrael.</hi> And for <pb n="96" facs="tcp:8696:56"/> this end is he good vnto vs. <hi>For all things are for your ſakes,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle)<note n="ſ" place="margin">2. Cor. 4.15</note> 
                  <hi>that the abundant grace might, through the thankeſgiuing of many, redound to the glorie of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Petition honoureth the Lord: but thankſgiuing more. Not ſimply in reſpect of the dutie: but becauſe our wants may haſten vs to ſeeke ſupplie: but if a man, after hee haue receiued what hee would, doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, with the leper,<note n="t" place="margin">Luk. 17.16.</note> to giue God thankes: it is moſt likely, that that is done, for God, without ſiniſter and by-reſpects.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> II. We haue nothing beſides to giue vnto the Lord. This was all that <hi>Dauid</hi> could finde, after hee had expoſtulated the matter, ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, with his owne ſoule,<note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 116.12,13,14.</note> 
                  <hi>What ſhall I render vnto the Lord, for all his benefits towards me?</hi> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion is, <hi>I will take the cup of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: and call vpon the name of the Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> III. It leadeth the couenant of God, as we may ſee in the Pſalmes, <pb n="97" facs="tcp:8696:56"/> 
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Pſ. 50.15.</note>
                  <hi>Call vpon me, in the day of trouble; I will deliuer thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me.</hi> Here the Lord bindeth himſelfe to vs, in a gracious coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to helpe vs in the euill day.</p>
               <p>And the Condition of this obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation is, that wee glorifie him, without which, what wee haue is no bleſſing: neither can wee looke for any other, but the next time to goe without.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> IV. And laſtly, It is the very crowne and life of our life. <hi>For in death their is no remembrance of thee,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt,<note n="x" place="margin">Pſ. 6.5.</note> 
                  <hi>In the graue who ſhall giue thee thankes.</hi> And <hi>Hezekiah,</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Iſa. 38.18.19.</note> 
                  <hi>The graue cannot praiſe thee, death cannot celebrate thee:—The liuing, the liuing, hee ſhall praiſe thee, as I doe this day.</hi> For this cauſe hee is thankefull for his life<note n="z" place="margin">Verſ. 20.</note>: And to this end,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſ. 118.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> deſireth to liue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>§. 4.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> The Kindes of prayer, and it is, 1. Legall. 2. Or Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of. 1. The Effects. 2. The ſubiect. 3. The Obiect. The vſes of this whole diſcourſe. 1. Why carnall men are not heard. 2. Vſe. How we may learne to pray.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The Kindes of praier follow. And it is either, 
<list>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:8696:57"/>
                     <item>I. <hi>Legall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. Or <hi>Euangelicall.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The Legall, which was required of <hi>Adam,</hi> in his ſtate of innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, can none of his fraile and dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate of-ſpring pray.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The Euangelicall, that is the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, qualified by the Goſpell, is the <hi>ſubiect</hi> of this diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>And the <hi>kindes</hi> of it may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in reſpect of, 
<list>
                     <item>I. The <hi>Effects.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. The <hi>Subiect.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. The <hi>Obiect.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Touching the <hi>Effects,</hi> there is a prayer of, 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>Senſe:</hi> when inſtantly that is accompliſhed, which is deſired: ſo <hi>Elias</hi> prayed, and preſently fire came downe from heauen,<note n="b" place="margin">1. Ki. 18.38</note> and conſumed the ſacrifice.</item>
                     <item>II. <hi>Hope:</hi> When we doe not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly receiue the good things we deſire: but doe, by hope expect them, 1. Ioh. 5.14.15. </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>For though the Lord doe ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, for many weightie cauſes, 
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:8696:57"/> take day with his children, for the performance of his promiſes: yet it pleaſeth him to giue them an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in hand: euen the earneſt of his Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In reſpect of the <hi>ſubiect:</hi> and firſt Perſonall; Prayer is, 
<list>
                     <item>I. Either wholly conceiued in the minde: As, it is moſt likely, <hi>Moſes</hi> his was. For the Lord ſaid to him,<note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 14.15</note> 
                        <hi>Wherefore cryeſt thou vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me?</hi> and yet the text doth not mention that he ſpake any thing.</item>
                     <item> II. Or expreſſed and vttered, withall, in words.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>And both theſe are, 1. Either continued exerciſes, 2. Or ſhort e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iaculations.</p>
               <p>And touching the locall ſubiect, prayer is, 
<list>
                     <item>I. Either publike: as in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
                        <note n="d" place="margin">Eſa. 66.23.</note> 
                        <hi>And it ſhall come to paſſe, that from the new moone to another, and from one Sabaoth to another, ſhall all fleſh come to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip before me, (ſaith the Lord).</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item> II. Or priuate: as in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, <pb n="100" facs="tcp:8696:58"/> 
                        <note n="e" place="margin">Matth. 6.5.</note>
                        <hi>But when thou prayeſt,</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>enter into thy cloſet, and when thou haſt ſhut thy doore, pray to thy Father which is in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Laſtly, touching the obiect, Prayer is for, 
<list>
                     <item>I. Either temporall bleſſings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone: as in that of <hi>Iacobs,</hi>
                        <note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 28.20.21.</note> 
                        <hi>If God will be with me, and will keepe mee in this way that I goe, and will giue me bread to eat, and raiment to put on, ſo that I come againe to my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe in peace.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item> II. Or for ſpirituall and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall: as in the Epiſtle of <hi>Iames,</hi>
                        <note n="g" place="margin">Iames, 1.5.</note> 
                        <hi>If any of you lacke wiſedome, let him aske of God.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item> III. Or for both: as in the Lords Prayer.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <div type="application">
                  <p>And thus much for the doctrine of prayer: The vſe of all may bee referred to two heads.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I. To let vs ſee why carnall men, (for we will begin with them) are not heard in their prayers. It is not poſſible they ſhould.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:8696:58"/>That a man may bee heard, at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time, theſe ſix things muſt ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily concurre.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. He muſt ſpeake.</item>
                     <item>II. To ſome.</item>
                     <item>III. His words muſt bee intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible.</item>
                     <item>IV. His voyce muſt be audible.</item>
                     <item>V. The meane betweene the ſpeaker, and the hearer, muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</item>
                     <item>VI. And laſtly, the hearer muſt ſet himſelfe to heare, as well as the ſpeaker doth to ſpeake.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Theſe doe not concurre ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, no, not one of them can bee found in the praiers of carnall men.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. They ſpeake not. For though their lips walke, and their mouthes vtter many words; yet are none of them true words of praier. Becauſe they doe not expreſſe that ſpiritual feeling, and gracious affection of the heart, which is required.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. Thoſe ſuperficiall, and liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe words which they vtter, are not ſpoken to God. Becauſe, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <pb n="102" facs="tcp:8696:59"/> they know him not at all: and ſo, make an idoll of him, or rather an idoll like him. Or knowing how he is reuealed in the Word, they cannot apply him to themſelues, as their God and Father in Chriſt: and otherwiſe hee is not the obiect of prayer.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. Their words are not intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible. Becauſe, 1. Either they come not neere themſelues, and their owne eſtate: as, confeſſing ſinne, they lay not theirs open, deſiring mercies; they conceiue, either not at all, or not aright, of their owne wants, &amp;c: 2. Or if they doe in termes, yet careleſly, or ſenſually; in a word, neuer ayming at the right ends of any thing.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. Their voyce is not audible: wanting the proiectiue power of Faith and Zeale, to ſend it into the Lords eares.</p>
                  <p n="5">V. The meane, betweene the Lord, and a carnall man, is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different. For looke how wide the Eaſt is fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Weſt, ſo far are they <pb n="103" facs="tcp:8696:59"/> ſeparated, yea further: For the Lord is infinitely diſpleaſed with him.</p>
                  <p n="6">VI. Laſtly, the Lord doth not ſet himſelfe to heare: nay, hee tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth away his eare, and hee will not heare. As hee ſaith by <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Eſa. 1.15.</note> 
                     <hi>When you ſhall ſtretch out your hands, I will hide mine eyes from you: and though you make many praiers, I will not heare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> II. The other vſe of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, is to teach vs, how to pray. Touching which, theſe ſixe things are to be conſidered.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. He that would pray, muſt be regenerate. Otherwiſe, he hath no acceſſe to God, nor abilitie to call vpon God, neither ſhall he finde ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with God.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. Labour for an order, and method. Of which ſomething hath beene ſpoken before.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. For matter, we muſt daily take a ſuruay of our eſtate. For our confeſſion, muſt bee exerciſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, either thoſe things wherein <pb n="104" facs="tcp:8696:60"/> the Lord is good vnto vs: or about thoſe euils wherinto we haue falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or whereunto wee are ſubiect, &amp;c. And this ſuruey muſt bee by the helpe of Conſcience.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. For words and termes, wee muſt ſearch the Scriptures, and reade the Formes of Prayer, ſet forth to the ſame purpoſe. And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre them to their proper heads: As for example.</p>
                  <p>Concerning God in himſelfe, we finde him thus ſet forth. 
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>God,</hi>
                           <note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 16.27</note> 
                           <hi>onely wiſe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item> 2. <hi>God,</hi>
                           <note n="k" place="margin">Act. 15.8.</note> 
                           <hi>which knoweth the harts.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item> 3. <hi>Whoſe is euery beaſt of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt,</hi>
                           <note n="l" place="margin">Pſ. 50.10.</note> 
                           <hi>and the cattell vpon a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand hills.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item> 4. <hi>From whom</hi>
                           <note n="m" place="margin">Iam.
1.17</note> 
                           <hi>commeth euery good gift, and euery perfect gift.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item> 5. <hi>Who onely hath immortality,</hi>
                           <note n="n" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.16</note> 
                           <hi>dwelling in the light, which no man can approach vnto, which no man hath ſeene, nor can ſee, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Concerning what he is vnto vs in Chriſt: he is ſaid to be. 
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Mercifull and Gracious,</hi>
                           <note n="o" place="margin">Exod. 34.6</note> 
                           <hi>long-ſuffering, <pb n="105" facs="tcp:8696:60"/> and abundant in goodneſſe and truth, keeping mercy for thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item> 2. <hi>The God of peace</hi>
                           <note n="p" place="margin">Rom.
16.20</note>.</item>
                        <item> 3. <hi>The God of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
                           <note n="q" place="margin">Ephe. 1.17.</note> 
                           <hi>the Father of glory.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item> 4. <hi>The Father of our Lord Ieſus</hi>
                           <note n="r" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.3.4.</note> 
                           <hi>Chriſt, the Father of mercies, and the God of all comforts, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth vs in all our tribulation.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item> 5. <hi>God euen our Father,</hi>
                           <note n="ſ" place="margin">2. The. 2.16</note> 
                           <hi>which hath loued vs, and hath giuen vs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting conſolation, and good hope through grace, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Concerning ſins, they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Decalogue, or tenne Commandements; (except thoſe againſt the Euangelicall comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, <hi>Repent and beleeue the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell</hi>), and are laid open euery-where in the Scriptures. And eſpecially, we may finde a multitude of them, heaped vp together by inductions, in theſe places, Pſal. 15. 1. Cor. 6.9. Gal.
5.19.20.21. Epheſ. 4.25.26.27.28.29.30.31. Coloſſ. 3.5.8.9. Iam. 3.14. Reu. 22.15. All <pb n="106" facs="tcp:8696:61"/> which, or any, to know how they concerne vs, we muſt lay them to our liues.</p>
                  <p>For the guilt of ſinne: wee are taught to confeſſe, 
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>That we are wretched</hi>
                           <note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 7.14.</note>.</item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Yea, wretched</hi>
                           <note n="u" place="margin">Reuel.
3.17</note> 
                           <hi>and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, poore, blind, and naked.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>O my God,</hi>
                           <note n="*" place="margin">Eſra.
9.6.</note> 
                           <hi>I am aſhamed: and bluſh to lift vp my face to thee, my God: for our iniquities are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed ouer our head, and our guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe is growne vppe vnto the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the puniſhment. 
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Thou, our God,</hi>
                           <note n="x" place="margin">Eſra.
9.13.</note> 
                           <hi>haſt puniſhed vs leſſe, then our iniquities de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>It is of the Lords mercies, that we are not conſumed,</hi>
                           <note n="y" place="margin">Lam. 3.</note> 
                           <hi>becauſe his compaſſions faile not.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>The wages</hi>
                           <note n="z" place="margin">Rom.
6.23.</note> 
                           <hi>of our ſinnes is death, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>For pardon. 
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Hide thy face from my ſinnes,</hi>
                           <note n="a" place="margin">Pſ. 51.9.</note> 
                           <hi>and blot out all mine iniquities.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>That he would blot out,</hi>
                           <note n="b" place="margin">Eſa. 44.22.</note> 
                           <hi>as a <pb n="107" facs="tcp:8696:61"/> thicke cloud our tranſgreſſions, and as a cloud our ſinnes.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>To goe ouer euery head, and at large, were too much for ſo ſmall a Treatiſe.</p>
                  <p n="5">V. We muſt digeſt theſe termes, into the order and forme propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to our ſelues.</p>
                  <p n="6">VI. Then the Spirit, putting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them the life of faith, maketh a prayer.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:8696:62"/>
            <head>A Three-fold Analyſis of the Lords Prayer.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A three-fold Analyſis of the Lords Prayer.</note>HAuing Finiſhed this ſhort diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe: becauſe the Lords Prayer is both the complete treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as likewiſe the abſolute pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of prayer, I haue annexed this three-fold <hi>Analyſis</hi> following.</p>
            <p>And Firſt, This is common to them all, That the prayer conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth of, 
<list>
                  <item>I. A Preface.</item>
                  <item>II. The body of Prayer.</item>
                  <item>III. The Concluſion.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Preface is contained in theſe words, <hi>Our Father which art in Heauen.</hi> Wherein is prefixed the <hi>Obiect</hi> of Prayer, <hi>God:</hi> deſcribed by that which he is, 
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>Relatiuely.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>Simply.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Relatiuely, to his Church: ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in generall, <hi>Father:</hi> and <pb n="109" facs="tcp:8696:62"/> applyed particularly, <hi>Our.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Simply, in himſelfe, <hi>Iehouah,</hi> that keepeth mercy and couenant, and <hi>El-ſhaddai, God all-ſufficient:</hi> both being inferred, by that hee is ſaid to be in Heauen.</p>
            <p>In the body of the prayer, are laid downe, 
<list>
                  <item>I. The Petitions: the ſpeciall obiects of our affections.</item>
                  <item> II. The Reaſons: The ſpeciall obiects of our Faith. 
<note n="*" place="margin">Not the reaſons ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, but that which may be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of God in them. For onely God is faiths obiect.</note> And theſe reaſons are three. 
<list>
                        <item>I. <hi>Kingdome,</hi> which reſpects the wel-ſpring and fountaine of all good things.</item>
                        <item>II. <hi>Power,</hi> which reſpects the meanes.</item>
                        <item>III. <hi>Glory,</hi> which reſpects the end.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For, (as the Apoſtle witneſſeth)<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 11.36</note> 
               <hi>Of him,</hi> (there is Kingdome) <hi>and through him,</hi> (there is power) <hi>and to him,</hi> (there is glory) <hi>are al things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:8696:63"/>The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion is in the laſt word, <hi>Amen:</hi> which is as much to ſay, as, 
<list>
                  <item>I. Lord, let it be as I haue prayed.</item>
                  <item>II. Lord, I beleeue it ſhall be ſo.</item>
                  <item>III. Lord, helpe mine vnbeliefe.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>All this, as I haue ſaid before, is common to all the three diuiſions. the varietie is onely in the ſixe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions.</p>
            <div n="1" type="analysis">
               <head>The I. Analyſis.</head>
               <p>The Firſt, is the common receiued Diuiſion of them into two threes. 
<list>
                     <item>The Firſt three concerning God.</item>
                     <item> The laſt three, our ſelues.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The ground of which diuiſion, is not, from the Efficient, or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor beſtowing theſe bleſſings. For, it is one and the ſame God, which halloweth his name, ſendeth his Kingdome, enableth to doe his will, giueth bread, forgiueth ſins, and preſerueth from euill.</p>
               <p>Nor from our Head, containing theſe good things for vs, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating <pb n="111" facs="tcp:8696:63"/> them vnto vs: For from the fulneſſe of one and the ſame Chriſt commeth all.</p>
               <p>Neither yet, from the finall cauſe, or end, either maine, for the Lord is glorified in both: or ſubordinate, for we are benefitted by both.</p>
               <p>But it proceedeth from the <hi>reall ſubiect,</hi> or <hi>obiect, viz:</hi> the things where-about our praiers in asking, and Gods grace in giuing, are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed.</p>
               <p>The firſt generall branch, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining God his, 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>Name.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>Kingdome.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. <hi>Will.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond, our, 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>Earthly neceſſaries.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>Sinnes committed.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. <hi>Dangers eminent.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>In the former, There is, 
<list>
                     <item>I. The End of all, beſides <hi>God;</hi> in the, 1. Petition.</item>
                     <item>II. The <hi>ſubiect</hi> of all happines from God: in the 2. petition.</item>
                     <item>III. The rule of all obedience <pb n="112" facs="tcp:8696:64"/> to bee performed to God: in the 3. petition.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>In the latter three, there is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, 
<list>
                     <item>I. The ſpace of repentance: in the, 4. petition.</item>
                     <item>II. The exerciſe of the grace of repentance: in the, 5. Petition.</item>
                     <item>III. The ſoueraigne preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of a Chriſtian, from euill, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter repentance: in the, 6. petition.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="analysis">
               <head>The II. Analyſis.</head>
               <p n="1">I. In the firſt petition is laid downe, the maine end of all to bee aymed at.</p>
               <p n="2">II. In the other fiue is laid downe the meanes: conſiſting in things which doe reſpect the hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of Gods name.</p>
               <p n="1">I. In this world: in all the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p n="2">II. In the world to come: in the ſecond petition: <hi>viz.</hi> the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealing the Kingdome of glory.</p>
               <p>All which doe concerne the life of a Chriſtian. And that, 
<list>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:8696:64"/>
                     <item>I. <hi>Simply.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>Reſpectiuely.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The things ſimply concerning the life of a Chriſtian, (to inſiſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe that reſpect this life) are, 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>Spirituall.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. <hi>Temporall.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The Spirituall are laid downe, 
<list>
                     <item>I. <hi>Cauſiuely,</hi> in the 2. petition.</item>
                     <item>II. <hi>Effectiuely,</hi> in the 3. petition.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The temporall, or earthly, are laid downe in the 4. petition.</p>
               <p>The Accidentall are ſuch as doe reſpect a Chriſtian, ouer and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the ſimple courſe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie, and the honeſt reſolution of his owne heart.</p>
               <p>The which are referred to two heads. 
<list>
                     <item>I. Pardon of euils committed: in the 5. petition.</item>
                     <item> II. Preuention of thoſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is in danger: in the 6. petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Heere, before I proceed to the third diuiſion, I would craue leaue to ſhew my opinion, concerning one obſeruation vſually collected, 
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:8696:65"/> from the methode of the three laſt petitions: namely, that there is, in them, an <hi>inuerſion</hi> of Chriſts me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode, recorded elſe-where, in the Scriptures: to wit,<note n="a" place="margin">Mat.
6.33.</note> 
                  <hi>Seeke yee firſt the Kingdome of God, and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and all theſe things ſhall be added vnto you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſpirits of the Prophets, are ſubiect to the Prophets: and I wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſubmit my conceit to the learned. To ſhew, then, what I thinke, I finde, heere, no inuerſion.</p>
               <p>For the things which concerne a Chriſtian ſimply, are to bee prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before thoſe that doe concerne him, but reſpectiuely and acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally.</p>
               <p>Now, in the 2. 3. and 4. petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are contained thoſe things which concerne him ſimply. In which three petitions, that other methode of our Sauiour, is moſt ſtrictly and preciſely obſerued. For what ſaith he?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seeke yee firſt the Kingdome of God,</hi> (that is laid downe in the 2. <pb n="115" facs="tcp:8696:65"/> petition, <hi>Thy Kingdome come</hi>): <hi>and his righteouſneſſe,</hi> (in the 3. peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Thy will bee done:</hi> For that is the righteouſnes of the Kingdome of God), <hi>and all theſe things ſhall be miniſtred vnto you:</hi> (in the fourth petition, <hi>Giue vs this day, our daily bread.</hi>)</p>
               <p>Where our Sauior brings a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. I. To the <hi>Graces</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of a Chriſtian: in the 2. petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. II. To the duties of a Chriſtian: in the 3. petition. III. And at the laſt, to the <hi>ſubiect</hi> wherein, and <hi>time</hi> when a Chriſtian is to exerciſe his graces, in the performance of the good workes which his <hi>God</hi> hath crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for him to walke in: that with comfort, hee may looke for that bleſſed hope,<note n="b" place="margin">Tit. 2.13.</note> and the glorious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of that great God, and our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Then, this poore Chriſtian, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to his calling, to exerciſe theſe good duties, findeth (contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the exaction of his God, and the reſolution of his owne heart, <pb n="116" facs="tcp:8696:66"/> which was to walke in all the good wayes of his God) that when he would doe good,<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> euill is preſent with him: In ſo much that the good he would doe, he doth not: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the euill which he would not doe, that he doth: by reaſon of the Law of ſin, which remaineth in his members. I ſay, this being ſo: Our Sauiour teacheth vs in the next place, to pray, <hi>Forgiue vs our treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And laſtly, becauſe, when ſinne committed is pardoned, wee are ſubiect ſtill to fall, in part: Satan continuing his malice, our Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiſh luſts (not being altogether extirpated and rooted out): and withal, our ſufficiency being whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of God; he addeth, <hi>Lead vs not into tentation, but deliuer vs from euill.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="analysis">
               <head>The III. Analyſis.</head>
               <p>In the ſixe petitions, are two things to be conſidered in generall.</p>
               <p n="1">I. The maine end of all to bee <pb n="117" facs="tcp:8696:66"/> aymed at: in the firſt petition.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The meanes whereby this end is atchieued: in the fiue petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons following. All which doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the perſon praying, or praied for. And in a three-fold reſpect: <hi>viz.</hi> of, 
<list>
                     <item>I. Our new man.</item>
                     <item>II. Our outward man.</item>
                     <item>III. Our old man.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Our new man, in the ſecond and third petitions. 
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Cauſiuè,</hi> in the 2. petition.</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Effectiuè,</hi> in the 3. petition.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Our Outward man: in the 4. petition.</p>
               <p>Our old man, to wit, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines of our corruptions, in the fifth and ſixth petitions: and that conſidered in reſpect of, 
<list>
                     <item>1. Sinne committed, to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned: in the 5. petition.</item>
                     <item>2. Euill eminent, to be preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: in the 6. petition.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>To come to a Mathematicall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, here is a <hi>ſphere:</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we may conſider, 
<list>
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:8696:67"/>
                     <item>I. The <hi>Center.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>II. The <hi>Lines.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>III. The <hi>Circumference.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The Center is the fourth petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For it is a ſubiect neceſſarily to be granted, in the firſt place, that a man muſt liue: otherwiſe, hee is not capable of the gracious dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Lord,</p>
               <p n="1">I. In reſpect of the new man, in viſiting him with his Kingdome of grace, to enable him to walke in the way of obedience to his will, through Ieſus Chriſt, vnto his Kingdome of glory.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Neither in reſpect of the old man, in pardoning ſinne paſt, or preuenting euill to come. All which doe inferre, that a man muſt liue.</p>
               <p>The lines are, I. <hi>Super-circuler,</hi> aboue the <hi>diameter.</hi> II. Or <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circuler,</hi> vnder the <hi>diamiter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The lines aboue the <hi>diamiter,</hi> are the 2. and 3. petitions.</p>
               <p>The lines vnder the <hi>diamiter,</hi> are the 5. and 6. petitions.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:8696:67"/>And theſe doe in oppoſition, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere one another, <hi>ex diametro.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third petition is, <hi>Thy will be done, &amp;c.</hi> The fifth petition, <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs our treſpaſſes, &amp;c,</hi> anſwereth it, on the contrary. For theſe treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes are diſobediences againſt the will of God, by way of omiſſion, and commiſſion.</p>
               <p>The ſecond petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, <hi>Thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome come:</hi> that is, the Kingdome of grace, in this world, and the Kingdome of glory, in the world to come.</p>
               <p>The ſixth petition anſwereth it, likewiſe, on the contrary: <hi>Lead vs not into tentation: but deliuer vs from euill:</hi> that is, the euill of ſinne, in this world, oppoſite to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of grace: and the euill of death, in the world to come, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Kingdome of glory.</p>
               <p>The circumference terminating the lines, and compaſſing the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is the firſt petition, <hi>Hallowed bee thy name.</hi> For the Lord doth ſend downe his Kingdome, for the <pb n="120" facs="tcp:8696:68"/> glory of his name: enable vs to do his will, for the glory of his name: forgiue our ſinnes, for the glory of his name: and deliuer from euill, for the glory of his name. And to conclude, he giueth temporall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, for the glory of his name.</p>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1. TIM. 1.17.</bibl> 
                  <p>Now vnto the King eternall, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, inuiſible, the onely wiſe God, be honour and glory, for euer and euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8696:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
